<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The hope of the faithfull Declaring breefely and clearly the resurrection of our Lord Iesus Christ past, and of oure true essentiall bodies to come: and plainly confuting the cheefe errors, that hath sprong thereof, out the Scripture and doctors. VVith an euident probation, that there is an eternall life of the faithfull, and an euerlasting damnation of the vnfaithfull. Nevvly imprinted and corrected. 1574.</title>
            <title>In sacrosanctum Jesu Christi Domini nostri Evangelium secundum Matthaeum commentariorum libri XII. English. Selections</title>
            <author>Bullinger, Heinrich, 1504-1575.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1574</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 192 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 128 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14943</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25250</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111633</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99835790</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99835790</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14943)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 335:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The hope of the faithfull Declaring breefely and clearly the resurrection of our Lord Iesus Christ past, and of oure true essentiall bodies to come: and plainly confuting the cheefe errors, that hath sprong thereof, out the Scripture and doctors. VVith an euident probation, that there is an eternall life of the faithfull, and an euerlasting damnation of the vnfaithfull. Nevvly imprinted and corrected. 1574.</title>
                  <title>In sacrosanctum Jesu Christi Domini nostri Evangelium secundum Matthaeum commentariorum libri XII. English. Selections</title>
                  <author>Bullinger, Heinrich, 1504-1575.</author>
                  <author>Coverdale, Miles, 1488-1568.</author>
                  <author>Werdmüller, Otto, 1511-1552, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 242, [8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Crede Lane, by Hugh Singleton, at the signe of the Golden Tunne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. 1574]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation by Miles Coverdale of selections from a German version of: Bullinger, Heinrich.  In sacrosanctum Jesu Christi Domini nostri Evangelium secundum Matthaeum commentariorum libri XII.</note>
                  <note>Wrongly attributed to Otto Werdmüller.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Future life --  Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10:1"/>
            <p>THE <hi>HOPE OF the Faithfull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Declaring Breefely and</hi> clearly the Reſurrection of OVR LORD IESVS CHRIST paſt, and of oure true eſſentiall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to come: and plainly confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the cheefe Errors, that hath ſprong therof, out the Scripture and Doctors.</p>
            <p>VVith an euident probation, that there is an eternall life of the Faithfull, and an euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting damnation of the Vnfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
            <p>Nevvly Imprinted and Corrected. 1574.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:10:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the Christian</hi> READER, GRACE and peace.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>VERYE MAN muſt needes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that this is novve a lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble time. In the vvhich the vvorld is not onli vnqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eted vvith vvars, dearthe, ſickneſſe and ſuch like but alſo ſtandeth euer more and more in greater pearill, thorovve vices euery vvhere bearing the ſvving. So that it is to be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red if vve banishe them not the ſooner, vve and our poſteritye shall yet come into farre greater ſorovv, then vve are already vvrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in. For if one should barely, and vvyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all rhetorical amplifications, but reherſe
<pb facs="tcp:10:3"/>
only the great pompe, vainglory, riot, forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, open idolatry, periury. &amp;c. of mighti men and rulers, vvhich vvaſt the vvorld mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably, the ſpace euen of many dayes vvold ſcaſe be any thing ſufficient thervnto. And vvhat heapes of vvickedneſſe priuate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons do adde vnto the ſame, all vviſe men ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ponder by themſelues. For if vve goe into our ovvne boſomes, vve finde that vve alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether vvill vvholy fashion and frame oure liues after the vvorld: ſeeking vaine pompe and priuate commodity for our ovvne luſte, vvith ſure shame and publike diſcommodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to others loſſe.</p>
            <p>VVhich all are vndoubted tokens, that the lavve and loue of God is litle eſtemed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs. VVhich vvith greeuous threates forbiddeth the foreſaid and other vices by ſtraight commaundement forſing, and ſure revvardes alluring vs to the contrary dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Neither may vve thinke, but that ſuche vices daily vvill encreaſe till the time they ouervvhelme vs, excepte the contempte of Gods la ve ſet apart, being the only ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent vvelſpring of all vvickednes, for vvhich the vvrath of God is inkindled, and his bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter curſes fall vppon vs the ſame vvorde be had in greate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> price and reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. For vvhy, vvhat godline<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e can be hoped for of them,
<pb facs="tcp:10:3"/>
vvhich hold nothing of God, the only foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of goodneſſe, and laugh his vvorde to ſcorne, of vvhom vve can knovve nothing, but that is there shevved vs: ſaue that ſmall knovvledge, that is of beholding of the crea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> vvhich neuertheleſſe declareth rather that there is a God, then vvhat he is, &amp; hovv he vvill be pleaſed. And though al the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſerue vs to enioy Gods bleſſings, yet as in a compound medicine, all the ſimples be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing holſom, ſome one may leſſe be ſpard the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the other ſo the article of reſurrection, clear and ofte inculcated in Sc ipture, is moſte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaileable, ſo that it vnknovvne, all vices ſvvarm and roſte in vs. For vve, not conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring our end, vvherein ſaluation &amp; life ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, or paines prepared for the accurſed, vvill but ſtaine our ſelues in voluptuouſnes. For vvho knovveth but the fleshe in this life, vvhy shold he not thinke, as good take it as leaue it, and beſt to make the moſte of that vvhich at laſt ceaſſeth. In this caſe the Ethnikes being ſaide: liue merely vvhile ye be in the vvorld: and eat vve and drink vve luſtely, to morovve vve shall die, vvhich all the Epicures proteſt openly, and the Italian atheoi in life practiſe, and no vvorſe man, then a Pope, in oure dayes hathe geuen the like definitiue ſentence, among his Courte
<pb facs="tcp:10:4"/>
deuines, of the ſoules immortality: the ſtory is knovven. Contrarivviſe, the learned in Goddes vvorde, knovving that this life is a death from ſinne, and a vvaye to the life to come, vvhich Chriſt vvith his croſſe hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened vnto them, for deſire thereof runne forth in the race of godlineſſe: aſſured of the revvard, ſith Chriſt, therfore bidding deathe battaile, that vve mought liue, hath broken her bondes and riſen againe. For goodes are not the poſſeſſors, as the Philoſopher ſaithe, and Chriſte alludeth in the parable of the tvvo ſtrong men, but the more valiant ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. VVherfore, gentle reader, I hauing this litle but abſolute vvorke of Chriſtes and our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, and that there is an eternall life and damnation, vvherin the deuill hath ſore aſſaulted the churche, by men, this only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, of greate authoritye and learning: thought it my duety, to put it in Printe, not keping that priuate, vvhich might doe ſuche good common. The matter is plain in ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: yet learne vve better things called in queſtion, and forced to vs by reſon. VVher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not to ſtirre vp Gods grace in vs by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braſing ſuche treatiſes, vvere to tempt God, and extincte the ſpirite.</p>
            <p>For the ſcholer learneth of his ſchole fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovv, that he perceiued not by his more ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:10:4"/>
maſter, and vnderſtandeth him euer af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the better: and ſo men forder one an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in ſcripture. VVhich as I meane in prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, if thou deſire in reading, the Lorde no nay shall graunt our requeſt: vvhich geueth bleſſings plentuouſly to all ſuche, as aske it conſtantly. To vvhom geue honor &amp; thank<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from heart, for the good that thou repeſt in his creatures.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>FARE VVEL.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <head>
               <hi>¶The firste parte of</hi> THIS BOKE, INTITLED THE HOPE OF THE FAITHFVL, vvhich entreateth of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection and Aſcenſion of Chriſte, vvith the frute and commoditye therof.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>THE FIRT CHAPTER. ¶The Contents of this boke, <hi>and the Authors purpoſe.</hi> 
               </head>
               <p>COnſidering that, by the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſts, and by all the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:10:5"/>
ther is nothing written more diligently, then touching the reſurrection of our lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt: my purpoſe is, ſome what more largely to talk of the ſame, and of the glorious aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his body into heauen: I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem of the reſurrection and aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of oure owne bodies: of the damnation of vnbeleuers, of the hope and eternall life of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. And this I mind to do, only vnto the honor, laude &amp; praiſe of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt: that the miſtery of the holy goſpell may be ſet forth &amp; opened to the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>moditye &amp; edifying of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and that of euery man it mai be plainly vnderſtanded, howe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:10:5"/>
greate things are prepared and geuen vs of Chriſt. This mater alſo doth ſpecially belong to the declaration of the holy Goſpell, foraſmuch as the beſt frute of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel is conteined and taughte therin. Therfore if I wryte ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght heerein more largely, I doe nothing that concerneth not my purpoſe. Yet I intende alſo to kepe a meaſure, &amp; not to open e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueri thing, that hereof might be wrytten, but only that which is cheefeſt, &amp; moſt neceſſary of all.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 2. That the Lord verely aroſe vvith his body.</head>
               <p>THat our lorde Ieſus Chriſt, with his owne very true bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, did verely ariſe from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dead,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:10:6"/>
it ſhalbe expedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t afore al thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs to teſtify &amp; proue. Therefore let the firſt witnes, euen our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfe, come forth now and beare vs recorde out of the Prophets, concerning hys true reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">Math. 12.</note> Like as Ionas (ſayth he) was three dayes and three nights in the whales bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſo ſhal the ſon of man be three dayes &amp; three nights in the hart of the earth. Nowe did not the fiſh caſt vp to the dry land ani o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for Ionas, but euen y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame Ionas himſelfe, whome he had ſwalowed. Therefore the verye ſame true bodi of the Lord alſo, that was buried, aroſe againe. Which thing the holye Apoſtle
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:10:6"/>
Paule minding perfectly to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pres, ſaid:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.</note> firſt of all I deliuered vnto you (or taughte you) that which I receiued: how y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt died for our ſinnes, agreing to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures: and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was buried, and that he roſe again the third dai, according to the ſcriptures.</p>
               <p>Lo, what can be ſpoken more euident and plain? He that died for our ſinnes, and was buryed, euen he himſelfe the very ſame roſe alſo againe. Of this now it foloweth, that the very true ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancial body of our lord did riſe againe: for euen the ſame died &amp; was buried. But to the entent y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it mighte the ſoner be beleeued, Paul the holy teacher declareth
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:10:7"/>
furthermore, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſpeaketh this according to the contentes of ſcripture, and that the ſame was taughte in the ſcriptures afore, meaning vndoutedly the lawe &amp; the Prophets.</p>
               <p>Neuertheleſſe, we will nowe bring forth the true and euident teſtimonies of the Angels, who in Marke,<note place="margin">Math. 28. Marke. 16. Luke. 24.</note> Luke and Mathew, ſpeake vnto the wemen y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> came to the ſepulchre: Ye ſeke Ieſus of Nazareth, him that was cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified. Why ſeeke ye the liuing among the dead? He is riſen, he is not heere. Beholde the place wher they had laid him. Reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber howe he ſpake vnto you, while he was yet in Galile, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:10:7"/>
that the ſon of man muſt be deliuered into the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of ſinfull me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and be crucified, &amp; the thirde day riſe againe. Therefore goe quickly, and tel this to his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is riſen from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deade. And beholde he ſhall goe before you into Galilee: ther ſhal ye ſe him, as he himſelfe tolde you.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the wordes of the Angels, which (if al circumſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces be thorowly well co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered) do plainly declare, that the very true body of the Lord did verely ariſe from the dead. The weme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> come &amp; ſeeke the body of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord, deſiring to annoynt it: therefore the queſtion is, touching the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſte. The Angels alſo
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:10:8"/>
ſpeake of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true body of Chriſt, &amp; make anſwer, ſaying: Ye ſeke Ieſus of Nazareth. Whervnto they adde diſtinctly, him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was crucified. Now are we ſure that his very true body was crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and died. He (ſay they) name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that died, euen Ieſus of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zareth, the ſame is become aliue againe. Why ſeke ye the liuing among the dead? The lord died of a truthe, but deathe muſt not haue dominion ouer him, nether muſte his body putrify or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, as other mens bodies doe, according as holy Dauid ſayde before:<note place="margin">Pſalme. 16.</note> Afore hand, I ſawe God alwayes before me: for he is on my right hand, that I ſhuld not
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:10:8"/>
be moued. Therfore did mi hart reioyſe, and my tong was glad. Moreouer alſo my fleſh ſhal reſt in hope, becauſe thou wilte not leaue my ſoule in Hell, neither wilte thou ſuffer thy holy one to ſee corruption. Thou haſt ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wayes of life, thou ſhalt make me ful of ioy w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance: and at thy right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, ther is pleaſure for euermore.</p>
               <p>Theſe words extend wholely vnto Chriſt, according as the .ii. excellent Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Actes. 2.13.</note> namely Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the ſecond, and Paul in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 13. of the Acts, do declare. Out of the Angels wordes alſo is it com into the articles of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> crede, as we all co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe words:
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:10:9"/>
he roſe again from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dead. This word (from the dead) doth truly expreſſe the death and reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion after this ſenſe. He died, as other men alſo doe, according to the law of nature. And euen in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame fleſhe, which he therefore toke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him that he might die, receiued the immortalitye and toke it vnto him againe. There<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore ſay the Angels: he is riſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> again. But that thing riſeth no vp, which fel not afore: therfore euen the ſame bodye of Chriſte, that fell in death, is from death riſen vp againe.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, they name alſo the place where he was laide, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe perfectly, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very true
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:10:9"/>
body was riſen, ſaying: beholde the place, wher they layed him. The mortall body of the Lorde hath his certaine place, yea his owne place (that the Logicians cal, <hi>Vbi,</hi> that is to ſay, where) in the which he was laide. And as he now is become immortal, he hath his own place againe. For if the bodye that was raiſed vp, were euery where, then had not the Angels ſayde: Beholde the place wher they laid him. Yea, they had not bene able to ſhewe any one place, wher he was not if the immortall body muſt be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery where. But now they ſhew a place, in the which the immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall body was not, and that with
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:10:10"/>
plaine expreſſe wordes, ſaying: he is not heere. Of this nowe it foloweth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the body of Chriſte. which is but in one place, did ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rely riſe again. In the goſpel o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſ. Iohn alſo the ſepulchre cloths wherin the Lord was wrapt (as the hed cloth, &amp; that which was about his body) are mencioned as ſtrong teſtimonies of the bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>di riſen vp: which clothes Pete<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Iohn did perfectly ſee. Fur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thermore, the Angels proue his very true reſurrection out of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> word of god, and ſay, remembe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> what he ſaide vnto you while h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> was yet in Galilee: the ſonne o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> man muſte be deliuered into th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> handes of ſinfull men. &amp;c. Wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:10:10"/>
theſe wordes will they inſtructe vs, that the ſonne of man, a very true body, is truly riſen againe. They ſay moreouer: go quickly, tel the diſciples, that he is riſen from death. Now was the body dead, and (as all mens bodies, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> die) laid in the graue. And euen y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame body was made immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, &amp; roſe again from the dead. He ſhall go before you into Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lilee, yea before you ſhal he goe, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a true bodi that moueth from one place to another: there, as in a certaine place, ſhall ye ſe him. Ye ſhal ſe him I ſay: for with a viſible &amp; palpable body is he ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, as ye are told by the Lorde himſelf, who can neither lie nor deceiue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:10:11"/>
               <head>CHAP. 3. Appearings of the body raiſed vp.</head>
               <p>HEreunto extende the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold appearings or ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wings of Chriſt, mencioned by the Euangeliſts. In Mark it is wrytten thus:<note place="margin">Mark. 16.</note> whan Ieſus was riſen early the firſt day after the Sabbothe, he appeared firſte to Mary Magdalen. To whom in the goſpel of Iohn, he ſayth: goe to my brethren and tel them:<note place="margin">Iohn. 20.</note> I go vp to my father and your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to my God and your God. Now whan ſhe came to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, ſhe tolde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſhe had ſene the Lord, &amp; that he had ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſuche things vnto her. In Mathew he meteth the wemen,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:10:11"/>
and ſayeth: All haile. Fear not,<note place="margin">Math. 28.</note> goe and tell my brethren, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they go into Galilee, there ſhall they ſee me. In holy S. Luke is me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion made of two appearings. The firſt when he ſhewed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the two that went to E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maus,<note place="margin">Luke. 24.</note> &amp; opened vnto them the true reſurrection of hys bodye. The ſecond, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were gon againe from Hieruſalem, they came to the Diſciples, minding to ſhew them, and to geue them to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, what they had ſene and hard. Then preuented they them, and ſaid: the Lord is truly riſen in deede, and hath apeared vnto Simon.<note place="margin">Luke. 24.</note> Nowe while they were talking of ſuche things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:10:12"/>
them ſelues, Ieſus ſtode in the middes of them, and ſaid: peace be vnto you. But whan they ſawe him, they were ſore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid, thinking y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they had ſene a ſpirit, or ſome other viſion. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaid the lord vnto them: why are ye troubled: And why doe thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghtes ariſe in your hartes? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold my hands and my fete.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 4. The body of Chriſt roſe again, not a ſpirite but a true body.</head>
               <p>NOwe that no man ſhould thinke it to be another body, which he had not afore his reſurrection, he addeth thereto immediatly: It is eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I my ſelf. Handle me, &amp; ſee: a ſpirite hath not fleſhe &amp; bones, as ye ſee me
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:10:12"/>
haue. And wyth that ſhewed he them his hands and his fete.</p>
               <p>With this euident teſtimony of the Lord,<note place="margin">De agone Chriſtiano. cap. 24.</note> was S. Auguſtine moued, boldly to ſaye, that they ought not to be heard, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the body of the Lord to haue riſen againe, as it was layed in the ſepulchre. For if it were not ſo, he wold not haue ſaide to his diſciples after the reſurrection: Handle me and ſee, for a ſpirite hath not fleſh &amp; bones, as ye ſee me haue. Now is it as much as to rob God of his honor, if anye man wold thinke, that the lord, who is the truth it ſelf, had in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing, that he ſpake, not ſayd the truthe. &amp;c. Thomas was not
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:10:13"/>
there, when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord ſhewed him ſelfe aliue vnto his diſciples: but whan he came againe, they told him with greate ioy, what they had ſene &amp; heard. Neuertheleſſe he thoughte it had not bene as they ſpake, and he ſayd: except I ſee in his hands the print of the nailes,<note place="margin">Iohn. 20.</note> &amp; put my finger into the holes of them, and my hand into his ſide, I will not beleeue it. Therfore after .viii. days, whan the diſciples were aſſembled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether againe, &amp; Thomas with them, Ieſus commeth in, while the dores wer ſhut, and ſtandeth in the middes among them, and ſaith: peace be vnto you. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde ſayde he vnto Thomas:
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:10:13"/>
reache hither thy finger, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde my handes, put thy hande here alſo and lay it in my ſide, &amp; be not faithleſſe, but beleuing. Thomas anſwered and ſaid vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him: my Lorde, and my God. For S. Paule alſo in the firſte chapter of the Epiſtle to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines doth out of the reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lord,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.</note> proue the god-head thus: which was borne of the ſeede of Dauid after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſh, and euidently declared to be the ſonne of god after the ſpirit that ſanctifieth, and by that he roſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain from the dead, namely Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt our lord. What ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be ſpoken more plaine, more euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or more certain? For freely did
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:10:14"/>
the Lorde ſette before their eies his body, which was ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the croſſe, that they might ſee it &amp; handle it. For the body was pearſed with nails, and marked with the printes therof. Oute of this now it foloweth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the lord with his true bodye did verelye riſe again, and not a ſpirit. And further, the Lorde alſo ſheweth himſelfe vnto the ſeuen, whych then were in Galile, fiſhing at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſea of Tiberias. The Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geliſt addeth likewiſe thervnto,<note place="margin">Iohn. 21.</note> that it was not expedient for any of the Diſciples to aſke him who hee was: for they knewe that it was the Lord. In the .28. chapter of Mathewe, the eleuen Apoſtles
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:10:14"/>
ſaw the Lorde,<note place="margin">Math. 28.</note> and worſhipped hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as it is declared afore. Some think, that the ſame was the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent appearing, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Paul ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of, ſaying: Afterward was he ſene of moe then fiue hundred brethren at once:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.</note> of whom many are aliue this day, but ſome are a ſlepe (or dead.) And in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame place dothe the Apoſtle make mention yet of two moe appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, ſaying: after this was he ſene of Iames, then to al the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles. And laſte of all he was ſeene of me, as of one that was borne out of due time.</p>
               <p>Luke the Euangeliſt, in the beginning of the Actes of the Apoſtles, hath in maner collec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:10:15"/>
all the probations together.<note place="margin">Actes. 1.</note> The Lorde (ſayeth he) ſhewed himſelfe aliue vnto his apoſtles after his Paſſyon, and that by manye tokens, appearing vnto them forty dayes, and ſpeaking of the kingdom of God. S. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter alſo, inſtructing Cornelius in the Faithe of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Actes. 10.</note> ſaid: we are witneſſes of all thyngs, which he did in the lande of the Iewes, and at Hieruſalem, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſlue &amp; hanged on tree. Him God raiſed vp y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> third day, and ſhewed him ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly, not to all the people, but vnto vs witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, choſen before of god for that intent: which did eat and drinke with him after he roſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:10:15"/>
With theſe plain probations &amp; teſtimonies (as I ſuppoſe it) it is euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly declared, and ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently ſhewed, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our Lord Ieſus Chriſt with his owne very true body, which ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged on the cros, did vereli riſe from the dead. As touching the glorificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I ſhal ſpeake therof, when I come to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſurrection of the bodies: and there will I ſhew more, that the glorification dothe nothing mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhe the veritye or truthe of the body, read the ſixt chapter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 5. The frute of the Reſurrection of Chriſte.</head>
               <p>NOw I wil declare the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, whye I haue w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:10:16"/>
ſuche diligence, and ſo earneſtly preaſed vnto this, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Ieſus chriſt w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his true body did truly riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. That is, how profitable &amp; neceſſary it is, ſo to beleue, and what frute the true reſurrection of Chriſt doth bring &amp; engender vnto vs. And albeit that hereof, as of a plentiful treaſure, muche might be ſpoken: yet wil I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend it all in a ſhort ſumme. Thoughe we be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plete &amp; made perfecte thorowe the deathe of Chriſt, while the iuſt iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of god is ſatiſfied, the curſe take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away, &amp; the penalty recompen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced and paid: Yet ſaith Peter, we are borne again, thorow the reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Ieſus Chriſt, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:10:16"/>
a liui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g hope. For like a chriſt with his reſurrection ouercame death, ſo ſtandeth alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> triumph &amp; victory of our faith in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of Chriſt. Therfore tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe his death is ſinne taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, by his reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſneſſe brought againe. For how could he w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his death, haue deliuered vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death, if he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf had of death ben ouercome? Or how could he haue obteined the victory for vs, if he had bene deſtroyed in the battell himſelf? Therfore thorow death is death diſcomfited, and with the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection is life to vs reſtored.</p>
               <p>Hereof commeth it that Paul ſayth: if Chriſt be not riſen,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.</note> then
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:10:17"/>
is your faith in vaine, and ye ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> yet ſtill in youre ſinnes: and ſo they, that be a ſleepe in Chriſte, are loſt. And to the Romaines Chriſt (ſayth he) was deliuered vp for our ſinnes,<note place="margin">Rom. 4.</note> &amp; roſe again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for our iuſtification.</p>
               <p>Heerevnto ſerueth it alſo, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wryteth in the.<note place="margin">Rom. 10.</note> 10. Chapter. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thou confeſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde Ieſus with thy mouth, and beleeue in thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hart, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God raiſed him vp from the dead, thou ſhalt be ſaued. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Philippians he ſayth more ouer:<note place="margin">Philip. 3.</note> I count al things but loſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for the excellent knowledge ſake of Ieſus Chriſte. Out of all this is there yet another thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, namely: that not onli life
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:10:17"/>
is reſtored vnto vs, but alſo that in the reſurrection of the Lord, the immortalitye of the ſoule is grounded faſte and ſure. For ſo ſayth the lord himſelf in the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell:<note place="margin">Iohn. 11.</note> I am the reſurrection and the life: he that beleueth on me, thoughe he were deade, he ſhall liue: and whoſoeuer liueth and beleueth on me, ſhall neuer die.</p>
               <p>Yet another frute alſo receiue we out of the reſurrection of the lord: namely that we are aſſured &amp; out of doute, euen as if we had receiued wryting &amp; ſeale therof, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our owne bodies likewiſe ſhal riſe from death: foraſmuch as in the true reſurrection of the body of Chriſt, oure reſurrection hath
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:10:18"/>
a faſt and vmnoueable grounde For Paule ſayeth: Chriſte roſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from the deade,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.</note> &amp; is become th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> firſt frutes of them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſleepe. Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by one ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> came death, &amp; by on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> man came the reſurrection of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dead. For as by Adam all die, by Chriſt ſhal all be made aliue but euery one in his own order<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The firſt is Chriſte, then they are Chriſtes. &amp;c. Now he that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt can not be alone: the hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> alſo ſhal not forſake the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Seing then y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt the head <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> riſen, it muſt needes folow, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> we alſo, as members, muſte ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> again. For euen in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame plac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> doth Paule conclude: if the dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> riſe not again, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is not Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:10:18"/>
riſen againe. And finally oute of the wordes of the holye Apoſtle Paul we learn,<note place="margin">Rom. 6 Colloſ. 3.</note> that thorow the enſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of Chriſte, that was rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vp, we are not onli prouoked to take vpon vs a new life, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we alſo thorowe the power of Chriſt are renued, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we mighte leade an innocent and holye life. And thus haue I breefely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded and declared the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall frutes of the reſurrection of the Lorde.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 6. Of the true Aſcenſion of the Lordes body, that aroſe a bodye and no Spirite, and of his place vvhether hee vvent to be in.</head>
               <p>MOreouer, it ſhall be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to know, to what
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:10:19"/>
place the true body of the Lorde was caried or came: whether it was laid in the earthe againe, or vaniſhed away, or turned into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nature of the Godhead, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe chaunged into a ſprite. In this poynt, we affirm thus: The right old Chriſtian faith, the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right holy ſcripture, &amp; the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Doctrine of the Chriſtian church, doth teach, hold, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fes, that Ieſus Chriſt, very go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, hath not laid away, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mixt together, nor yet put of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> natures, the godhead &amp; the ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hode: but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he kepeth ſtil bothe natures in theyr properties v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>blemiſhed, &amp; that he aſcended v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to heauen very true God &amp; ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:10:19"/>
For ſo we knowledge and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes in the Crede: he aſcended vp to heauen. We finde alſo in the goſpell of Marke: ſo then, when the Lord had ſpoken vnto them,<note place="margin">Marke. 16.</note> he was receiued into heauen, &amp; ſitteth on the right hand of god. Item Ruffinus an olde wryter (who hath declared the articles of the faith) ſaith:<note place="margin">Ruffinus.</note> he aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded into the heauens: not thether where the worde, that is God, was not afore (for he was euer ſtil in hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen and continued in his father) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut thether wher the word, that became man, ſate not afore. Yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>il we declare this more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel of Luke,<note place="margin">Luke. 24.</note> wher <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t is written thus: and he led the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:10:20"/>
out into Bethanie, &amp; lifte vp hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> handes, and bleſſed them. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> came to pas, as he bleſſed them he departed from them, and wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> caried vp into heauen.</p>
               <p>Nowe if thou ponder euery thing heere thorowly, thou mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> needes acknowledge, and bein<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ouercome wyth the truthe, tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> muſt nedes confeſſe, that the ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry true body of the lord was n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> layd away, neyther turned int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the nature of the godhead: but h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a very true ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who at one ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> is but in one place, aſcended a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> was taken vp into heauen, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to one place. He led them out<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſaith he. Who? I prai the. Eue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Lorde Ieſus, whiche vnto
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:10:20"/>
than, by the ſpace of forty daies, had in very deede truely ſhewed himſelfe vnto his diſciples, that he was riſen from the dead with a very true eſſencial body. Euen he, the very ſame that had taken vnto him a true bodi, led his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples out vnto Bethanye, &amp; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence brought he them farther to Mount Oliuet. And in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame place, lifting vp his handes (no doubt, bodely &amp; humain hands) yea with the prints &amp; tokens of the woundes, he bleſſed them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>amely his diſciples: that is, he ſaluted them, as the maner is of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hoſe that take their leaue of vs. And ſo departed he from them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſet his body corporally in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:10:21"/>
as in one place. For after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward it foloweth yet more plai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: he departed from them: that is, he was caried into heauen.</p>
               <p>For, to be caryed, may heare be ſpoken, only of the body: and in ſuche ſorte departed he from them, that his body was fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth taken vp into heauen.</p>
               <p>And though all this be euiden<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and plain in it ſelf, yet by the E<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uangeliſt Luke,<note place="margin">Actes. 1.</note> in the Actes o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Apoſtles, it is ſet forthe an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> opened more manifeſtly. For a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore all things he teſtifieth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Lord aroſe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his owne true b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy: and that by the ſpace of. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> daies, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> many tokens &amp; euide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces, he plainli proued &amp; declar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:10:21"/>
his reſurrection vnto the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. And immediatly he addeth therevnto, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euen the very ſame body was taken vp into heauen. For whan he had ſpoken theſe things (ſaith he) while they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held him he was take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp on hie: and a cloud receiued him vp out of their ſight. Lo, the Lord was taken vp: yea euen in their eye ſight was he taken vp on hie, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a cloud receiued his very true body away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſight of their eyes. I beſeche you, what can be more aptly or more conuenientli ſpoken of an eſſencial body?</p>
               <p>It foloweth farther in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſt Luke: and while they loked ſtedfaſtly vp towards hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:10:22"/>
as he went (mark that wel) beholde, two men ſtode by them in white Apparell, which alſo ſayd: ye menne of Galilee, why ſtand ye gaſing vp into heauen? This ſame Ieſus, who is taken vp from you into heauen, ſhal ſo come, euen as ye haue ſeene him go into heauen. Wherfore oure Lord Ieſus is departed vp into heauen, with his own true eſſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiall body: yea euen w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſame which he raiſed vp from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dead. For euen w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſame very true humaine bodye ſhall he come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain vnto iudgement, according as the Lord himſelfe ſayd, &amp; the Prophet Zachary,<note place="margin">Math. 26. Zach. 12. Iohn. 19.</note> whoſe words ſ. Ihon aledgeth: They ſhal loke
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:10:22"/>
on him, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they haue pearſed.</p>
               <p>Thus I truſte it is ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proued and declared, that the Lord Ieſus, with his own very true bodye which he raiſed from deathe, is gone vp into heauen. But to the intente that no man miſtake this worde (heauen) or otherwiſe imagine any thing, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is darke or not vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the ſimple being in erroure, may ſcaſe know at the laſt wher heauen is, or where Chriſt hath his dwelling: It ſhal therfore be nedeful, brefely to declare, what the heauen is: and that the Lord w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his own true body doth dwell in heauen, as in one place. For heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is a certain aſſured place,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:10:23"/>
and not only a name &amp; declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the eſtate &amp; being in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. Therfore whan it is ſayde, Chriſt is gon vp into heauen, it is not ſo much as only to ſay, he hath taken vpon him an heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſtate or being: but alſo, he dwelleth bodely in heauen, as in one place.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 7. The diuers ſignifications of this vvord, Heauen, as it is vſed in ſcripture.</head>
               <p>THis worde (Heauen) in the ſcripture, is vſed diuers and ſondry waies. Firſt for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> firmament, which is called th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> heauenly hoſt, or beutifull appa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rell of the heauens. Hereof ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thou recorde in the eighte an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ninetenth Pſalme.<note place="margin">Pſal. 8.19.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:10:23"/>It is taken alſo for the ayre which is aboue vs, as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſayeth: he couereth the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen with clouds,<note place="margin">Pſal. 146.</note> to prepare rain for the earth. Hereof co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth it, that the foules, which flie in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ire, are called foules or birdes of heauen, that is to ſay, birdes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the aire. Item, heauen alſo is vſed for a ſeat, habitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or dwel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing, as: the Lord hath prepared his ſeate in heauen, and:<note place="margin">Pſal. 103. Math. 5.</note> ye ſhall not ſweare by Heauen, for it is Gods ſeat. And though God be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nfinite, &amp; can not be compaſſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bout w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any place (as the moſte wiſe Salomon ſaide:<note place="margin">3. Reg. 8.</note> The hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, and the heauens of all hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, are not able to conteine
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:10:24"/>
thee. And howe ſhould then th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> houſe doe it, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I haue builded? Yet the ſcripture calleth the he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is aboue vs, a dwelling <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God: which dwelli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g is ordein<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for all faithfull &amp; vertuous bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uers, and is named the heaue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> This doth Paule witneſſe, ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing, we know,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.</note> that if our earth manſion of this dwelling wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> deſtroied, we haue a building <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God, an habitation not made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hands, but eternall in heauen.</p>
               <p>Here is now heauen taken f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the kingdom of God, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome of the father, or ioy &amp; ete<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nal life, which is peace and re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> The heauen (I ſay) is a ſeat a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dwelling of the faithfull or ble<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:10:24"/>
beleuers: a determinat place alſo, into the which the lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus was receiued, when he was taken vp into the heauen. And this dothe the ſcripture plainly declare vnto vs, namely y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aboue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ther is a certain determinate place prepared for vs.</p>
               <p>For Luke ſaith: he was recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed vp on hie,<note place="margin">Actes. 1.</note> and a cloude toke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im vp away out of their ſighte. Item, and while thei loked ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſtly vp towardes heauen, the Angels ſaide: this ſame Ieſus, which is taken away from you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nto heauen, ſhal ſo come, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e haue ſene him go into heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ho is ſo ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t now, that he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>otteth not where heauen is or
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:10:25"/>
the clouds, or into which heau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Apoſtles loked ſo ſtedfaſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Beſides this, the holye Apoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Paule ſayth alſo: our conuerſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">Phillip. 3.</note> freburgerſhip or dwelling in heauen: from whence we lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for the Sauioure, euen the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Ieſus. Loe in heauen, ſaythe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Apoſtle, is oure dwelling. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which heauen, I pray you? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in the ſame whence we loke the ſauioure. Now is it euid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from whence we wait and lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſeing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Apoſtle ſayth ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> we, which ſhall liue and rema<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhalbe caught vp with them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the cloudes,<note place="margin">1. Theſſ. 4.</note> to mete the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the air, and ſo ſhall we eue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wyth the Lord.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:10:25"/>He ſaith alſo in another place: if ye be riſen againe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſte,<note place="margin">Colloſ. 8.</note> then ſeke thoſe things which are aboue, wher Chriſt ſitteth at the right hand of God. And therfore is the Lord Ieſus gone vp into the heauen that is aboue vs, and namely into y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſure certai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> place, which is prepared for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bleſſed.</p>
               <p>And in the ſame heauen, as in a ſure certain place, doth Chriſt now dwel bodely.</p>
               <p>Of this opinion alſo was holy <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> as in dede it is righte &amp; agreeable vnto holy ſcripture. His words are fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in the boke <hi>ad Dardanum de praeſentia Dei.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Fulgentius</note> Holye <hi>Fulgentius</hi> in the ſeconde booke that he wrote vnto King
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:10:26"/>
Traſimundus, is earneſt to bring euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto this vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding: that the humaine kind &amp; nature of Chriſt, which now dwelleth in heauen, is circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, &amp; in one place. With him a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo accordeth vniformly the holy martyr <hi>Vigilius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vigilius.</note> whoſe teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny I wil now omit, and come a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gaine to the holy ſcripture.</p>
               <p>The Scripture, minding t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhewe what is become of the bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy, that roſe againe from death and aſcended vp, and where h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hathe his dwelling, ſaith ſimpl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; plainly:<note place="margin">Chriſt ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth at the right hand of God.</note> he ſitteth at the righ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hand of God the father almig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tye. Thus nowe is the bodye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt come to the right hand
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:10:26"/>
God, there ſitteth he. But heere ſhall it be expedient to declare what the right hande of God is, and what it is to ſit at Goddes right hand.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 8. VVhat Gods right hand is, and to vvhom it is referred.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, the right hande of God is not referred vnto god him ſelf, but vnto men, that are on the right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. So that firſt the right hand of God dothe ſignify the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal ſaluation, and the place of thoſe, that be ſaued. This did ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li Auguſtine teach, whoſe words I may well alledge, foraſmuche as he alſo doth confirme &amp; proue his opinion by the diuine and holye Scriptures. In his booke
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:10:27"/>
                  <hi>de Agone Chriſtiano,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt. de agone Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtiano. cap. 26.</note> he ſayth: we ought not to heare them, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the ſonne to ſitte at the righte hand of God. For they ſay, hath god the father alſo a right or lef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſide, as bodies haue? Nether d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> we vnderſtand that of the father For with no bodelye proportion can God be deſcribed or compre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hended. As for the right hand o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the father, it is nothing els but eternall ſaluation, which he ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> geue to al godly &amp; faithfull bele<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uers. In like manner is the left hande rightly taken for the euer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>laſting damnation, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhall com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vpon the vnbeleuers. So y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of God, but of the creatures <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> muſt be expounded, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is writte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:10:27"/>
of the right &amp; left hand. For euen the body of Chriſt alſo, which is the church, ſhall come to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right hand, that is, into ſaluation, as the Apoſtle ſaithe to the Epheſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans:<note place="margin">Ephe. 2.</note> he hathe raiſed vs vp toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him, &amp; made vs ſit toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him among them of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. For though oure bodies as yet be not there, our hope neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe is there already.</p>
               <p>The ſame holy Auguſtin ſaith alſo further in the boke <hi>De fide &amp; ſymbolo.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De fide &amp; ſymbolo. cap. 7.</note> By the right hand (ſaith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e) muſt be vnderſtand the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wher rightuouſnes, peace &amp; ioy is: like as the gotes alſo ſhalbe ſet on the lefte hande. That is, by reſon of theyr ſins &amp;
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:10:28"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:10:28"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:10:29"/>
wickedneſſe, they ſhal come into great calamity, troble &amp; miſery All theſe are the wordes of holy Auguſtine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 9. VVhat it is to ſit at the right hand of God, hovve Chriſt ſitteth the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and vvhat he dothe.</head>
               <p>ANd thus now, to ſit at th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> right hand of God, is eue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as much, as to be in reſt: that to ſay, al wretchedneſſe &amp; miſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſet aſide, to liue in a godly life, to be partaker of eternall ioy Now that this word (to ſitte) vſed in Scripture for reſt, the places declare. In the. 4. boke Moiſes it is wrytten thus: ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> your brethren go to war,<note place="margin">Num 32.</note> &amp; wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ye ſit here?<note place="margin">Mich. 4.</note> And in Micheas: eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:10:29"/>
one ſhal ſit vnder his vine and figtree. &amp;c. Mani mo ſuch places ther be. Wherfore now, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſcripture ſaithe, that the lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſitteth at the right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of his father, it vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth it chefely of his humaine nature: which he he toke vpon him, that the ſame being diſcharged and free from al trauaile and miſery of man, is now all in ioy, &amp; partaker of the kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euerlaſting. Thus ſaithe alſo Rufinus in his expoſition of the Crede:<note place="margin">Rufinus.</note> to ſit at the right hand of the father, is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient for the manhead receiued, which is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued thorow a miſtery. For to aſcribe that to the diuine nature, it is vnſeemely, as though it had
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:10:30"/>
a ſeate in heauen: but of the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine nature it is properly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand and ſpoken.</p>
               <p>And the like yet did holy ſ. Pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter teach afore Rufinus time, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it is to ſee in the Actes.<note place="margin">Actes. 2.3.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But now might one aſk wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> doth the ſon at the right hand o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the father? Muſt he alway ſitt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> there, &amp; be aſmuch as made faſt and bound vnto it? Anſwere.</p>
               <p>The Lord Ieſus, after his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine nature that he tooke vpon him, &amp; which he put not fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him in heauen, hath now eternall ioy with his elect: he as the head w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his members ruling &amp; reigning with all faithfull beleeuers for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore. Wherof we ſhal ſpea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:10:30"/>
more afterward.</p>
               <p>A very ſuperfluous &amp; vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table queſtion alſo is it, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one will ſo curiouſly inquire &amp; know what God doth in heauen.</p>
               <p>For God wil only teach vs w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his holy worde, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he liueth &amp; ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth eternally in the glory of his heauenly father. Holy Auguſtin ſaithe alſo in the booke <hi>De fide &amp; ſymbolo:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De fide &amp; ſymbolo. cap. 6.</note> To go about for to ſeke and inquire, where and howe the body of our Lord is in heauen, it is a poynt of nice people, &amp; brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth no profit.</p>
               <p>Only we ought to beleue, that he is verely in heauen. For truly it ſtandeth not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our weaknes, to comprehende and diſcerne the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:10:31"/>
priuity of the heauens: but it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemeth our faith, to haue the wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thy &amp; glorious body of the Lord in highe and worthy eſtimation. Hetherto Auguſtine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 10. That Chriſt ſitteth at the right hand of God by his humanity, but circum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcribed in place, and is not euery vvhere.</head>
               <p>NOw though the heauenly honor &amp; glory be high, and may not be expreſſed: yet th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> place where he dwelleth, is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, &amp; the bodye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is in heauen can not be euery where. For the right hande of God, in and after this firſt ſignification thereof, is not infinite. Els muſt al faithf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> beleuers alſo, &amp; they that are ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, be euery where, ſeeing they
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:10:31"/>
are with the ſonne of God, who is taken vp into heauen. For the Lord himſelfe ſaithe:<note place="margin">Iohn. 17.</note> nowe from henceforth ſhall I be no more in the worlde, but they are in the world, &amp; I come vnto thee. Vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this he ſaith: father, they whome thou haſt geuen vnto me, I will that where I am, they alſo be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> me, that they may ſee my glorye which thou haſt geuen me.</p>
               <p>Item, he that doth me ſeruice let him folowe me:<note place="margin">Iohn. 12.</note> and where I am, there ſhal alſo my ſeruaunts be. Seing now that our ſoules &amp; oure bodies alſo, after the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the fleſh, ſhalbe in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, as in a place certain: it folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth that the body of the Lord,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:10:32"/>
which into heauen is taken vp, hath alſo a place certaine in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the right hand of God in this ſignification can not be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery where.</p>
               <p>In this vprighte matter, let it trouble no man, that is read in ſ. Paul,<note place="margin">Ephe. 4.</note> how y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt aſcended vp aboue al the heauens by meanes whereof, a curious body mighte peraduenture conclude: if Chriſt our Lord be taken vp aboue the heauens, then can there no place certain be aſcribed vnto him, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there is no place aboue or w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out the heauen. Neither ought it to offend any man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is wrytten, how y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vnto Chriſt ther is geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a name, which is aboue al names.
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:10:32"/>
Or that Paule ſayth,<note place="margin">Phillip. 2. 1. Cor. 2.</note> howe that no eie hath ſene, neither any eare heard, nor is come into the heart of man, what god hath prepared vnto them that loue him.</p>
               <p>For the ſcripture of God tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row out, doth witnes conſtantly and ſure, that Chriſt Ieſus is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vp into heauen, &amp; ſitteth at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of his father. Wherby it is out of dout, that the Apoſtle thought not to ſet Chriſt w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>oute heauen: but therefore proponeth he the matter w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo high &amp; excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent wordes, to ſhew and declare vnto vs, that the body of our lord which afore was deſpiſed, and ſhamefulli defaced, is now in the ſupreme &amp; higheſt glorye, &amp; that
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:10:33"/>
meaneth he, where he ſaythe, a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>boue all heauens. For who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dothe thorowly conſider y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> plac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Paule to the Epheſians, fin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Paul hath ſet two parte of his oratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Ephe. 4</note> the one againſt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> other. For firſt he ſaithe thus that he aſcended, what meane<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it, but that he alſo deſcended fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> into the loweſt parts of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth Againſt this, ſetteth he nowe: h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that deſcended, is euen the ſam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> alſo that aſcended vp, euen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>boue all heauens.</p>
               <p>Therfore is here the one ſet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainſt the other: namely, to de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cend into the loweſt parts of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> earth, &amp; to aſcend aboue all he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uens. But who would heere co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clude:
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:10:33"/>
Chriſte aſcended into the loweſt partes of the earth: <hi>Ergo,</hi> he had no place vpon earth? For euery man vnderſtandeth well, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Paule with theſe words minded to declare the true comming of the Lord vpon earth, &amp; the great humility &amp; mekenes of our lorde Ieſus Chriſte. Therefore, who wold the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the other part of the oration conclude: Chriſt aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vp aboue all heauens: <hi>Ergo</hi> he is not in heauen, or in anye other place? For is there alſo any one place without the heauen: Who vnderſtandeth not now, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Paule here minded to ſay nothing elſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that, which he vttereth more plainly to the Philippians:<note place="margin">Phillip. 2</note> he
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:10:34"/>
hathe exalted him on hie? An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thoughe this highe or heauenl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> honor be greater and more glor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous, then any mannes tonge ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or may expreſſe: yet the heaue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is and doth remain ſtil the dwe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling of the faithful, and therefor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is it a place certaine.</p>
               <p>Wherfore after my plaine an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſimple vnderſtanding, whych i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not curious, I beleue conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the glorified body of Chriſte i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> aſcended vp aboue all heauens that is aboue al co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pace, or ſpher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; height of heauen, &amp; ſo euen i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> heauen, that is in the dwelling <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the faithful, and ther remaineth and is not (as they ſay) paſſed b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> on the out ſide of heauen.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:10:34"/>For the truthe witneſſeth eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently: where I am,<note place="margin">Iohn. 12.</note> ther ſhall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo my ſeruaunts be. Nowe ſhall the ſeruauntes of God be in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, &amp; not without or aboue the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (that is to ſay) in no place. For Paul, the choſen ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of god, ſaithe to the Philippians:<note place="margin">Phillip. 3.</note> oure dwelling is in Heauen, from whence we loke for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſauior. &amp;c. plainly alſo &amp; euidently doth the true worde of God declare, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the heauen, into the which Chriſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended, is a place certain: for the Lord ſaithe: in my fathers houſe are many dwellings: if it were not ſo, I would haue told you. I goe to prepare a place for you.<note place="margin">Iohn. 14.</note> And if I goe to prepare a place
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:10:35"/>
for you, I wil come to you again &amp; receiue you euen vnto my ſelf that where I am, there you may be alſo.</p>
               <p>Here in dede could nothing b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> brought forthe more mete &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenient to oure purpoſe. For th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we now treate of, is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> heauen, which is the dwelling natiue country of the bleſſed, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which here is called a dwelling or manſion, or place: yea a dwe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling &amp; place in the houſe of Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father. Who is now any mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſo malapart or arroga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, as to v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dertake to deny, that heauen is place? For thus ſaithe the Lor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> In my Fathers Houſe alread<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> there are many manſions: th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:10:35"/>
not only I, but al mine alſo haue a place and dwelling.</p>
               <p>If it were not ſo, then had I told you, that I wold goe to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the ſame for you. But now it is not needefull, ſeeing they be prepared alredy, &amp; wait for you.</p>
               <p>Wheras I now go away, and muſt be from you a litle ſeſon, it is not that I wold prepare man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions for you, for they are prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red already: but that I thorowe my death may make the way for you into Heauen, and open the ſtrete to the ſaid dwelling. Now to the intent no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal ſay, that we haply haue a place in heauen as men, but Chriſt hath not ſo a place: therfore doth the truthe of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:10:36"/>
god plainly expreſſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the place, wher chriſt is, is a place in dede.</p>
               <p>For he ſayeth: I will take you vnto me:<note place="margin">Iohn. 14.</note> yea not onely vnto me, but vnto my ſelf. For immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, doth he yet add it more plaine: That wher I am there you may be alſo.</p>
               <p>Chriſt then, as a very true mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is in Heauen, as in one place wherfore it foloweth, that we a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo ſhall be in Heauen, as in o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> place certaine. This the truth ſayth: therfore muſt it needes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> euen ſo, &amp; can be none otherwiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame alſo doth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> human kinde and nature require whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God, as Auguſtine ſaith, did e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>due with immortality, but too<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:10:36"/>
not away the nature and kinde.</p>
               <p>The Seleucians,<note place="margin">The Seleu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cians error.</note> or Hermians denyed our ſauiour Chriſt after the fleſhe to ſit at the right hand of the father. But the true faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full beleuers haue euer ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed and taught, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the very true body or fleſhe of our Lord dothe ſit at the fathers right hand. For verely if the bodi and fleſh of our Lorde haue not his place geuen him, or if that be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>drawne from him: then is this the plaine mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, that our Lorde had no true body. For holy Auguſtine ſaith, and ſaith right: take all roume &amp; place from the bodies, that they haue no place to be in, and then are they no where: if they be no
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:10:37"/>
where, then are they nothing at all. As for the place of Paule to the Philippians in the ſeconde Chapter, it teacheth nothing at all, that, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the exaltation and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion of Chriſte, any thing is withdrawn from the nature hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we oughte to ſpeake nothing more of it, or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhuld or mighte aſcribe no name and place vnto it: but like as with y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> words goi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g before (which ſerue much to the matter) he thoughte to expreſſe the loweſt humilitye of Chriſt, euen ſo is it nowe hys minde, with very honorable and hie excellent words, to ſet forthe his glory.</p>
               <p>Yea he declareth himſelf in the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:10:37"/>
words folowing, and ſaith: in the name of Ieſus ſhall all knees bow,<note place="margin">Phil. 2.</note> bothe of things that are in heauen, of things that are on the earth, and things that are vnder the earth.</p>
               <p>And thus hath the father exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the name of Ieſu aboue all names,<note place="margin">The name of Chriſt is aboue all names.</note> euen in ſhewing and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring, that Ieſus is the ſame, whom al they that are in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vpon earth, and vnder the earthe ought by right to know, worſhip and feare, as Lord of al things &amp; creatures: yea, &amp; that all things ſhuld confeſſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Ieſus is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord, to the praiſe of god the Father.</p>
               <p>For verely we muſte needes knowledge that Ieſus Chriſt is
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:10:38"/>
lord, yea lord of all things, king, defender &amp; redemer, of like pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and honor with the Father. Which thing extendeth not to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fathers derogatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or diſhonor, as the Arrians foliſhly thought:<note place="margin">Arriani.</note> but to the great glory of the father.</p>
               <p>The Lord ſaith himſelf in the goſpel:<note place="margin">Iohn. 5.</note> the father hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted all iudgement vnto the ſonne, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld honor the ſonne, euen as they honor the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. He that honoreth not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſon, the ſame honoreth not the father which hath ſent him.</p>
               <p>Moreouer there he ſaithe: and now glorify thou me, O father, with thine own ſelf,<note place="margin">Iohn. 17.</note> with y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> glori which I had with thee, or euer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:10:38"/>
world was. From the beginning had he y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> honorable name of god, which is glorious and far excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent aboue all names.</p>
               <p>Now thorow the incarnation, and by reaſon of the contemned and deſpiſed croſſe of Chriſt, the godly honor in Chriſt was thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghte to be ſomewhat darkened. But that did the father reſtore &amp; bring to glory, in that he raiſed vp his ſon from death, and tooke him vp into heauen. And thus gaue he him a name, which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all names: for ſo he decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is Lorde of all things.</p>
               <p>Holy Peter alſo, a felowe hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of S. Paule, in the ſeconde chapter of the Actes of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:10:39"/>
did in like maner vtter the ſame.<note place="margin">Actes. 2.</note> For after he hathe opened &amp; declared the true reſurrection of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt from deathe, &amp; his glorious aſcention into heauen, he ſaith: ſo therfore, let all the houſe of Iſrael knowe for a ſurety, that God hath made this ſame Ieſus, whom ye haue crucified, Lord &amp; Chriſt. And to be ſhorte: Paule by the name of Chriſt, that is aboue all names, vnderſtode the bleſſed name of God the Lord, which can not be vttered, and is aboue all names.</p>
               <p>But ſeing our Lorde is a true man, like as he is alſo very God both together, and hath with the glorification not put of the kinde
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:10:39"/>
and nature of man, nether conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it thorow the godhead: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore remaineth he ſtil a true crea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is, a very true man, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore may he alſo right wel be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med after the ſame nature, and hath likewiſe a place certaine.</p>
               <p>Finally, as for the words of the Apoſtle Paule (the eye hath not ſene, and the eare hath not hard,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.</note> neither haue entred into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heart of man, the things which God hathe prepared for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that loue him) theſe wordes, I ſay, muſte not be referred to the place of thoſe, that are ſaued. For they are wrytten of the vnoutſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble greatneſſe of the ioye, as the whole text of the wordes ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:10:40"/>
doth declare.</p>
               <p>Brefely, foraſmuch as it is op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and manifeſt vnto vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Lord Ieſus Chriſt after his nature y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he toke vpon him, is a very true man in glory: It foloweth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the true humain body of Chriſt hath his owne place, whereof I hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hetherto ſpoken ſo much, not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out cauſe: namely, to the inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> godly perſones may know, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this is a place certain prepare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for them in heauen: and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> may conſtantly beleue, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen they haue a brother, namel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord Ieſus Chriſt. Touching the frute of the Aſcenſion of o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lord, I ſhall more largely ſpeak of it afterward.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:10:40"/>
               <head>CHAP. 11. An other ſignification of ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at the right hand of God, by vvhich maner of ſitting Chriſte is euery vvhere, ſitting there in ſuch ſorte after his God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heade.</head>
               <p>THus come I againe to the former part, what the righte hand of God ſignifieth, &amp; is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. It is taken in the ſcripture for ſtrength, protection, power, and for the incomprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſible ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor or glory. And therefore it is wrytten: thy right hand, Lorde,<note place="margin">Exod. 15.</note> is become glorious in power, thy right hand hath al to daſhed the enemy. Item in the Pſalme: Thou haſt geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me the defence of thy ſaluation,<note place="margin">Pſal. 18</note> thy right hand alſo ſhal hold me vp. Moreouer:<note place="margin">Pſal. 118.</note> The right hand of the lord hath
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:10:41"/>
the preheminence, the right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of the Lorde bringeth mightye things to paſſe. After this ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the right hande ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the name to ſit, to rule, to gouerne, to defend, to behaue hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe as a prince or Regent dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently in his office, &amp; faithfully to execute the ſame. For in the thirde boke of the kings, ſaithe Dauid:<note place="margin">3. Reg. 1.</note> Salomon ſhall ſit vpon my ſeat, &amp; ſhall reigne after me. And ſo in the Pſalme he ſaithe: the Lord ſaid vnto my Lord, ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thou at mi right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,<note place="margin">Pſal. 110.</note> til I make thine enemies thy foote ſtoole. And Paule ſaith: Chriſte muſte raigne,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.</note> till he hath put all his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies vnder his fete. Item in
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:10:41"/>
the Prophet Zachary:<note place="margin">Zach. 6</note> behold y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> man whoſe name is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> braunch, and he, that ſhal ſpring vp after him, ſhall build vp the temple of the Lord, yea euen he ſhall build vp the temple of the lord: he ſhal beare the praiſe, he ſhal ſit vpon the Lords throne, &amp; haue the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination. A prieſt ſhal he be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo vpon his throne. This kinde of ſpeche is taken of the vſe and cuſtome of Kings and Princes, which haue their Deputies, to whom they frely geue all aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to rule and gouern. Euen ſo is Chriſt, in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the father will be honored, &amp; thorow his autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritye &amp; power is it his pleaſure to rule. He is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:10:42"/>
hand of the father, that is to ſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to haue the dominion or gouer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nance in heauen &amp; in earth: an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this commiſſion is geuen hy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> faithfully to execute, &amp; to be lor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and gouernor of all things.</p>
               <p>Thus the right hande of Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is infinite, neither mai it be ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in, for Gods mighte &amp; power<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> incomprehenſible: the kingdo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Chriſt alſo, whych is euerl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſting, is a kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of al worlde, &amp; ſo is he of one ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, of o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> power &amp; honor with the fathe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not bounde to one place, but euery where, who in all thing ruleth and worketh: ſeing he not only a very true man, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſo the very true God, after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:10:42"/>
ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>hode finite, but after his god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head infinite, and incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, and that in one vndeuided perſon he conteineth very true God and man, King and Lorde of al things. For S. Peter ſaith Chriſte is at the right hande of God, gone vp into heauen,<note place="margin">1. Peter. 3.</note> aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, mighte and power, being ſubdued vnto him.</p>
               <p>Item Paule to the Epheſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: God the father raiſed vp Chriſt from the dead, and hath ſet him on hys right hande in heauenly things aboue all rule, power, might and domination, &amp; aboue al names that are named, not in this worlde only, but alſo in the world to come. And hath put all
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:10:43"/>
things vnder his feete, and hath made him aboue all things: the head of the congregation which is his body, &amp; the fulnes of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that filleth al in al things. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> much concerning the right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of god, and concerning heauen that is the place certain or dwe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling of the bleſſed: in the which alſo our lord Ieſus with his bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy hath his manſion and ſeat.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 12. The frute and commoditye the corporall aſcenſion of Chriſt, both<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that he doth novv for vs, and in that w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> learne by it.</head>
               <p>AFter this from he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce fort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> will I ſpeake of the frui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and profit of the corporal aſcen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, of his ſeat and place at the righ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:10:43"/>
ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of his father. Afore al thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs we muſt knowe, that our Lorde aſcended vp with his very true body, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he as mediator betwene God &amp; man (being very God &amp; ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> himſelf) &amp; high prieſt in his owne te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, might be before his heauenly father, make interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for vs, &amp; wholy take vpon himſelf our neceſſities &amp; grefes. For Paul ſaith to the Hebrues: Chriſt is not entred into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy places that are made w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hands,<note place="margin">Heb. 9.</note> whych are ſimilitudes of true things: but is entred into the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry heauen, to appear now in the ſight of God for vs. Herevnto al ſo pertein other ſentences or te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies of Iohn in his firſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle.<note place="margin">1. Iohn. 1.2.</note>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:10:44"/>
Item of Paul to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> wherin he ſaith: Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſame, did our Lorde aſcend vp bodely, that he, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hys fleſh taken vp into heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, might ſtay &amp; direct vpon the holy go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all worſhipping and Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of thoſe that are his. For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> corporal worſhipping dothe fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hence forth pleaſe him, but ſuch as is done to his ſpiritual body He ſaith in the goſpell of Iohn the pore haue you alwaye wy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you,<note place="margin">Iohn. 12.</note> and whan you wil, you m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> do the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> good:<note place="margin">Mark. 14.</note> but me haue ye n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> alway. Hereunto alſo ſerueth ſaying of Paule: althoughe w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> haue known Chriſt after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſh yet know we him ſo no more.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 5.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:10:44"/>Moreouer, the Lord with his reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath taught vs, that we alſo ſhuld lift vp our mindes into heauen, ſeking no ſaluation at all vpon earth, ſeing that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen is our right natiue country. Therefore oughte we to vſe the world, as though we vſed it not,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.</note> and to directe all oure care and thoughte vnto heauenly things. For Paule ſayth to the Coloſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans:<note place="margin">Coloſ. 3.</note> ſet your affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on things which are aboue, &amp; not on thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs which are on earth. For ye are deade, and your life is hid wyth Chriſt in god.<note place="margin">Phillip. 3.</note> Item to the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippians: our dwelling is in hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen, from whence we loke for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſauior, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ieſus chriſt our lord.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:10:45"/>Chriſt alſo with his aſcenſion into heauen, thought to declare vnto vs his power and mighte, wherin conſiſteth our ſtrength our power, richeſſe, triumphe a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainſt ſinne, death, world, deuil, and hell.</p>
               <p>For he aſcending vp on high led captiuity captiue, and wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he had ſpoiled the ennemies, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> gaue gifts vnto his people, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> endueth them yet daily w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tual riches.<note place="margin">Ephe. 4.</note> Therefore ſitteth h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> now on highe, to the intent tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with his owne ſtrengthe, whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he daily beſtoweth vpon vs, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> may regenerate vs into a ſpir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tual life, &amp; quicken vs w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſprite, garniſhing his church
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:10:45"/>
that is to ſay the faithfull, wyth manifold gifts of thanks, defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them againſt all euill, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing the terror of hys enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, but preſeruing and ſauing vs, as thoſe that truely do honor and worſhip him. For he, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the victorious triumph, is the king, ſauioure, and heade of all faithfull beleuers.</p>
               <p>Finally, alſo with his reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, he hathe prepared vs a place, &amp; made the way, &amp; opened it into heauen. Thus in heauen hath he placed the true ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that we mighte haue an aſſured true teſtimoni, that our fleſh alſo ſhal riſe againe, and that the whole perfect man, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> body and ſoule,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:10:46"/>
ſhalbe caried into heauen. For me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers ſhalbe like vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heat. Therfore, as the cloud toke vp y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very true body of the Lord, ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> euen the whole perfecte manne Chriſt: ſo ſhal all godly perſons be taken vp into the air to mete the Lorde, that they may liue w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt their Lorde &amp; head for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore. For Paul ſaith: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dead in Chriſt ſhall ariſe firſt.<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 4.</note> The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> we, which liue &amp; remain, ſhalb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> caught vp with them alſo in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cloudes, to meete the Lorde i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ayre, and ſo ſhall we euer b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with the Lord.</p>
               <p>Item to the Hebrues: by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> meanes of the bloud of Ieſu, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> haue free entrance into the hol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:10:46"/>
place by the new &amp; liuing way,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.</note> which he hathe prepared for vs thorowe the vaile, that is to ſay, by his fleſh. Vnto this meaning agreeth very wel, the godly and excellent ſentence of the old an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient wryter <hi>Tertullian,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tertullian.</note> who in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> booke of the reſurrection of the fleſh, ſaith thus: Chriſt, which is called the arbiter and mediator betwene God and men, hath, of the ſame that is ſet and commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto him of both, reſerued al ſo vnto himſelf, the adding to of the fleſhe, for an earneſt peny of the whole ſumme.</p>
               <p>For like as he hath left vs the pledge of the ſprite, euen ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe hath he receiued of vs
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:10:47"/>
the earneſt peny of the fleſh, and caried it vp with him into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, a true euidence or pledge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he will bring thether alſo the whole ſumme, bodye &amp; ſoule. &amp;c. For this great and highe bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite, declared vnto vs by hys di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine mercy, without oure deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, be laude and praiſe, honor and thankes vnto oure King, our victorious Triumpher, head and Redemer, euen our Lord Ieſu Chriſt, from hence forth now, and for euermore.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:10:47"/>
            <head>¶<hi>The ſecond part,</hi> ENTREATING OF our bodies.</head>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 13. Of the true Reſurrection of oure Fleshe.</head>
               <p>NOwe commeth it to the poynt, that we muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſpeake of the true raiſing vp of our bodies, or reſurrection of this our fleſh: for the ſame folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth out of the reſurrection and aſcenſion of oure Lorde Ieſus Chriſt. This worde (to riſe vp)
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:10:48"/>
as Tertullian <hi>De Reſurrectione carnis</hi> declareth, extendeth to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto that which was falne. For nothing ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ariſe, ſaue onely it that fell. For when a thing was falne, and ſtandeth vp againe, we ſay, it is riſen, for aſmuch as this terme, to riſe vp, hath a relacion. S. Paule vſeth the word <hi>Aniſtemi</hi> which ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to erecte, to riſe vp, to ſet vp againe, and to ſtand. <hi>Egeromai ex hypnou,</hi> I riſe vp and awake fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſlepe. The Hebrues vſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde <hi>kum,</hi> which ſignifieth, not onli to riſe vp, but alſo to endure to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, and to remaine vpright.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ioſua. 7.</note>For in the booke of Ioſua we read: the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Iſrael coulde
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:10:48"/>
not ſtande before their enemies, that is, they might not endure &amp; continue before them. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more in the boke of Geneſis: eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry thing was deſtroyed that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained (y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is,<note place="margin">Gene. 7</note> whatſoeuer there was, and ſtode vprighte or erec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it ſelfe) vpon the face of the earthe.</p>
               <p>Heereof it commeth, that to ſtande vp, and to rayſe vp, is called the immortality, or the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting and perpetuall conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of the ſoule.</p>
               <p>As whan the Lord ſaith in the goſpel of Iohn: I will raiſe him vp at the laſt daye.<note place="margin">Iohn. 6</note> For if by the laſt day the houre of euery mans death be vnderſtand, then dothe
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:10:49"/>
the Lord raiſe vp (that is, he pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerueth) the ſoule in the ſtate, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it dieth not, neither periſheth in death: nowe if by the laſt day, be vnderſtand domes day, then rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth he vp the body from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth at the laſte daye in the generall iudgement.</p>
               <p>Therfore the words, to ſtand vp &amp; raiſe vp, ſignify eyther the conſeruation of a thing, which is, that it be not deſtroyed and peariſhe: or elſe the reſtoring of a thing, that was fallen to hys right caſe and eſtate againe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 14. Our flesh, or body it ſelf, shal riſe againe, though it be hard to beleue, and vvhat the flesh or body is.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:10:49"/>NOwe will we ſpeake alſo of theſe termes, fleſhe &amp; body, or corps. We beleeue the reſurrection of the body or fleſh. The ſcripture commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly calleth it the reſurrection of the dead: to declare euidentli, that the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection muſt not be referred to the ſoule, nor to the ſpirite, but directly vnto the body and to the fleſhe. <hi>Cyprianus</hi> or <hi>Ruffinus</hi> ſayth, that the church towardes the Weſt, did expreſſe &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the article in the holy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolical Crede, after this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: I beleue the reſurrection of the fleſh. And ſo they added ther vnto manifeſtly this term (the) to the intent that no man ſhould
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:10:50"/>
vnderſtand any other fleſh, ſaue only the ſame natural and eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall fleſh, which we cary about. So ſaithe Auguſtine alſo in the boke of the Articles of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Crede: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſame viſible, which properly is called fleſhe, ſhall without all dout &amp; aſſuredly riſe vp againe.</p>
               <p>Me thinketh that Paule the Apoſtle minded to poynte vnto the fleſhe, as with a finger, and therefore ſayde:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.</note> this corruptible muſt put on incorruption.</p>
               <p>With the terme (this) poynteth he as w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a finger vnto our fleſhe.</p>
               <p>Holy Hierome forceth and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pelleth Iohn, the biſhop of Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, to confeſſe and know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge the reſurrection, not onely
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:10:50"/>
of the body, but alſo of the fleſh, and ſayeth: the fleſh and the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy are two things.</p>
               <p>Euery fleſh is a body,<note place="margin">VVhat the bodye or corpes is called of the Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtes.</note> but eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry body is not fleſhe: namely, a wal is a body, but fleſh it is not.</p>
               <p>For fleſhe is properly called a ſubſtaunce of blonde, ſynowes, bones and vaines ſet together. As for a body, though the name thereof alſo be vſed for fleſh, and moſt part for a ſubſtance y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> may be ſene or handled, yet it betoke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ſometime a ſubtile ſtate, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> can neither be handled nor ſene. As namely, the aire.<note place="margin">It is harde to beleue the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</note> But at all times it hath bene a hard thing for man to beleue, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodies which are buried &amp; reſolued to
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:10:51"/>
corruption, ſhuld wholely, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out imperfection or blemiſhe, be brought againe, and reſtored.</p>
               <p>Therfore the Athenians, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they heard of the holy Apoſtle, the reſurrection of the dead, thei mocked and laughed his doctrin to ſcorne.</p>
               <p>For who wold lightly credite that the bodies, which nowe are corrupt &amp; returned to earthe, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> otherwiſe torne, and deuoured o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wild beaſtes &amp; foules, yea ſonn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> time bre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and brought to aſhes, or drowned with water, ſhould perfectly be brought again, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wholy reſtored? But God, wil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling to make that eaſy &amp; lighte, which is harde vnto vs, hathe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:10:51"/>
the reſurrection of our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt ſet before our eies an open, plain, and ſure trial, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration or euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the true vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>douted reſurrection: whervnto, as to an enſample &amp; ſure ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth of the reſurrection, we ought to haue reſpect, aſmuch and as oft as we thinke vpon it, and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der howe our bodies ſhould riſe againe.</p>
               <p>Therfore with ſo many teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies and arguments haue I declared afore, that Chriſte our Lorde with his owne body roſe truly againe from death. He ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried vp Helias alſo liuing body and ſoule into heauen, and mani <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne raiſed he vp from the deade,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:10:52"/>
that we concerning the reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of the dead, ſhould haue vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly no doubt at all.</p>
               <p>Finally, with plain &amp; euident teſtimonies of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture, hath he opened and ſhewed as I now wil declare: which teſtimonies and arguments truly do teache, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the fleſh of men ſhal riſe again from the dead: that is, that oure bodies ſhal at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt day be truly raiſed vp vnto iudgement. Holy Iob ſaith thus in the .19. Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:<note place="margin">The true reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the flesh pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</note> O that my words now were wrytten: O that they wer put in a boke: wold God they wer gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen with an iron pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Lede, or in ſtone to continue. For I am ſure that my redemer liueth, &amp;
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:10:52"/>
that he ſhall ſtande ouer the duſt (or earth) in the later dai: that I ſhalbe clothed againe wyth this ſkin, &amp; ſee God in my fleſh. Yea I my ſelfe (or for my ſelfe) ſhall beholde him, not with other, but with theſe ſame eies. Mi reines are conſumed within me. Iobs aduerſaries complained of him,<note place="margin">Antagoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtai Iob.</note> as though he knewe not God, &amp; as though he ſet nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g by him. Vpon this great ſlander &amp; blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, he anſwereth, and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth his faith, deſiring that hys belefe were wrytten in Lede, &amp; in hard ſtone: that is, he wiſheth his faithe to be knowne to thoſe that come after, which he alſo declareth with few words, after
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:10:53"/>
this maner: I am of you co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vpon &amp; accuſed, as though I knew not God: now do I know right well in my heart, yea &amp; I beleue, &amp; am certified aſſuredly, that my redemer or auenger li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth. Here Iob vſeth an Hebrue worde called <hi>Goel,</hi> which ſome expounde a redemer: it ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a reſcuer &amp; an auenger, ſuch one as is a more frend of oures, ſuch as were they, to whome in the law of the Iewes, it apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined to redeme the goods and to reſcue them, as we may learn farther out of Ruthe, and of the fourth boke of Moſes:<note place="margin">Ruth. 4. Num. 35.</note> and with the aforeſaide name <hi>Goel,</hi> dothe Iob ſet forth and ſpecify y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:10:53"/>
our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, that he liueth: namely, that he is the true liuing God, the life &amp; reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of men, and that he is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the reſcuer and aue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, dout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe euen the ſame that is oure very nere frend: namely a very true ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſuch one as hath taken our own fleſh &amp; bloud vpon him, ſuffered death, &amp; with his death hath made vs liuing.</p>
               <p>Moreouer he ſaith: at the laſt ſhall he ſtand ouer the duſt. For our Lorde Ieſus, with his very true body, ſhall come at the laſt day to iudge, and then ſhall he ſtand ouer the duſt. This ſaying declareth euidently, that he will vndertake and doe ſomewhat:
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:10:54"/>
namely, that he ſhall put to his mighty hand, ſo order and bring to paſſe, that the duſt ſhall come to life againe. The duſt calleth he here our fleſh,<note place="margin">Gene. 3.</note> and that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſcripture. And wyth this doth he wonderfull well ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth of our fleſh: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that our very owne true fleſh ſhall riſe againe.</p>
               <p>For he will certify vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euen the very ſame bodi, which at the firſt was made of duſt, and now into duſt is ſowne, &amp; thorow the corruption is becom duſt agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yea euen that ſame very body &amp; none other, ſhalbe raiſed vp.</p>
               <p>But to the intent that no man ſhuld draw or referre the duſt to
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:10:54"/>
any other thing, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the body of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: It foloweth moreouer in holy Iob, that after they (name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the father, the ſon, &amp; the holy goſt) haue with my ſkin (not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a ſtraunge, but with mine owne ſkin) clothed the body, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mine owne body, which I nowe haue called duſt (&amp; therby vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth he the fleſhe, the ſinowes &amp; the bones) then ſhall I ſee God in my fleſh: that is, fully and per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fectly ſhall I be reſtored &amp; made whole again. For to ſee God, is nothing els but to be partaker of eternall ioy &amp; ſaluation. And to ſe god in, or fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fleſh, is to be taken vp corporally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to euerlaſting ioy. Beſides this,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:10:55"/>
he dothe yet more euidently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the perfectneſſe of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the fleſh, and faith: Whom I for my ſelfe ſhal ſee (y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is, to my commodity and ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) mine eies ſhal ſee him, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I my ſelfe ſhal ſe him, and none other for me. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which words it is principalli to be noted, that he ſayth, I ſhal ſe him, yea eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I my ſelfe. Then, mine eyes ſhall ſee him. Finally, I and els none other. As he wold ſay: euen I y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> now haue true fleſh and bone, &amp; loke nowe vpon you wyth mine eyes, ſhall w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the very ſame eyes beholde God alſo. Therefore in the reſurrection of the deade, we ſhal, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the eſſenciall ſubſtance &amp;
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:10:55"/>
nature, be euen the ſame that we were before deathe: namely we ſhal haue our members, as hed, eyes, bones, belly, armes, legs, hands, fete. &amp;c. Now wher this diſtinction is, there muſt be alſo circumſcription, there muſt the ſame haue compace and limits. It followeth yet farther in Iob: my reines (namely my deſire &amp; luſt) are waſted away and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med within me: that is, wyth in me, namely in my hart, are cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all other deſires, luſtes and pleaſures, in compariſon of this my hope towards the reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: yea in compariſon thereof, thei al are nothing, neither wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be eſtemed. For in the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:10:56"/>
Reſurrection reſteth all my hope and delite.</p>
               <p>So ſayde Paule alſo: I haue counted all things but loſſe, and do iudge them but dunge,<note place="margin">Phillip. 3.</note> that I mighte winne Chriſt, to knowe him, and the vertue of his reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</p>
               <p>And therfore the olde tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of the boke of Iob hath euill interpreted theſe wordes after the ſenſe: this hope is layed vp in my hart.</p>
               <p>After all this, dothe holy Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> adde herevnto, that maketh the vnderſtanding perfect, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth his ſaying, thus: Seing I this knowledge &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fes, why holde ye me for vngodly? Why
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:10:56"/>
do ye perſecute me and vexe me thus with ſpiteful wordes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proche and ſlaunder? Yet is the roote of the worde found in me. And he calleth the roote of the worde, the right foundation and grounde of godlineſſe. As if he woulde ſay: foraſmuche as the true head article of ſaluation is found in me.</p>
               <p>For like as the rote geueth al vertue &amp; ſap vnto the tre: euen ſo is the matter of the reſurrection of the dead thorow Chriſte, the cheefeſt, greateſt, and true prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal poynt of the worde and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of God. Repent therfore (ſayth Iob) for wrath handleth or dothe nothing righte, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:10:57"/>
prouoketh god vnto venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. The prophet Eſay in his twenty ſixe chapter doth teſtifie the Reſurrection <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner:<note place="margin">Eſay. 26.</note> Thy dead ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e, euen w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my body ſhall they ariſe. Stand vp &amp; be glad, ye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> reſt (or dwel) in the duſte: for the dewe of the herbes is thy dew, &amp; the ground of tyrants ſhalt thou caſt down. Thy dead O god (ſayth the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet) ſhal liue, nameli the ſoules of thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> for thy ſake are ſlaine, and that haue worſhipped thee. Neuertheles, their bodies ſhall not preuent my body in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection: but at the laſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or vpon domes daye ſhall they riſe againe with my body?
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:10:57"/>
Likewiſe ſaith alſo S. Peter, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſoules of ſuche,<note place="margin">1. Peter. 4.</note> as died afore time, do liue with god, but with the fleſhe they ſhalbe iudged as other men. Therfore did the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Prophet Eſay beleue &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the general reſurrection of all bodies at the laſt day. In the which Reſurrection, he openly knowledgeth, that his own bodi alſo ſhal riſe againe. Afterward bringeth he in an Archangell blowing the tro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pet, and ſaying: ſtand vp &amp; be glad, ye that reſt in the duſt. To reſt in duſt, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing els but a deſcription of mans body.<note place="margin">To reſt in the duſt.</note> For the ſoules and ſprites do not reſt or lie in duſt: but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodies are buried therin,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:10:58"/>
&amp; become duſt. Therfore me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſubſtance &amp; ſtate therof, wherin they riſe againe, are called inhabyters and I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> dwellers of duſt, or ſuche as reſt in duſte.</p>
               <p>The declareth he with a ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude, how our bodies, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> putri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy and corrupt, ſhal thorowe the power of God from deathe and corruption be eaſely raiſed vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</p>
               <p>The power of god, that char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth &amp; commaundeth vs to riſe vp from death, doth he compare to the dew: which wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it falleth downe, quickeneth and reuiueth the dead herbes. Likewiſe alſo dothe the power of God to oure
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:10:58"/>
dead bodies, which it quickneth and raiſeth vp again. Contrary to this he ſetteth another ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, ſaying: the earth of tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts that is, the bodies of tyrantes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>halt thou raiſe vp, O God: but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hou ſhalt caſt them downe, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, thou ſhalt ouerthrowe them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nto hell and eternall paine.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, touching the true <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſurrection of oure bodyes, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſion of the Prophet Ezechiel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ſo euident and plaine,<note place="margin">Eze. 37.</note> that it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s not nedefull to ſpeake oughte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>herof.</p>
               <p>And of this haue we many te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>timonies and witneſſes in the Prophets, whych mighte heere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ell haue ſerued: but ſeing it is
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:10:59"/>
not neceſſary, I haue, becauſe of ſhortneſſe, omitted them, &amp; now will I come to the ſentences of the new Teſtament.</p>
               <p>The Lord ſaith: Verely, vere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I ſay vnto you:<note place="margin">Iohn. 5.</note> the houre ſhal come, and now it is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the deade ſhal heare the voice of the ſon of God, and they, that heare it, ſhal liue. And immediatly after he ſaith: the houre ſhal come, in the which all they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> graues ſhall heare his voyce, and ſhall come forth. Now is it manifeſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> neither the ſoules nor ſprites, but the bodies are in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> graues And if other bodies ſhoulde riſe vp for oures, what needed he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye to make mencion of the
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:10:59"/>
graues: But to the inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that he, immediatly in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpell, mighte declare the euident, plain, &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oubted reſurrection of oure bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ies: he forthwith, by his migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y and wonderfull power,<note place="margin">Iohn. 11.</note> raiſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p Lazarus fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death, who now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id ſtinke, and had line .4. dayes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the graue. This maruellous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct had the lord himſelf declared <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nto Martha with theſe words: by brother ſhal riſe again. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſwered ſhe: I know y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe in the reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at the laſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ny. Lo how commen, manifeſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd knowne vnto euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e general reſurrection of oure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>odies? The Lorde ſaithe more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nto Martha: I am the reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:10:60"/>
&amp; the life, he that beleueth on me, though he were dead, yet ſhall he liue. And euery one, that liueth and beleueth on me, ſhall neuer die.</p>
               <p>But what nedeth me to collect ſo many teſtimonies of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the deade, conſidering that the Apoſtles were vpon no article more feruent and earneſt then vpon this? He, that will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge all the ſentences &amp; witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, muſt wryte out almoſte the whole new teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Luke ſaith in the Actes of the Apoſtles:<note place="margin">Actes. 4.</note> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> greate power did the Apoſtles beare witneſſe of the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Lorde Ieſus Chriſte. And in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame boke ſaith Paul:
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:10:60"/>
or the hope and reſurrection of the dead, am I iudged.<note place="margin">Actes. 23.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And yet againe:<note place="margin">Actes. 28.</note> for the hope ſake of Iſrael, am I bound with this chain. In many places hath the holy Apoſtle Paule brought forth euident enſamples and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies of oure reſurrection, concerning the whych we ſhall ſpeake in due time.</p>
               <p>He ſaith moreouer: we,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.</note> which liue, are alwayes deliuered vnto death for Ieſus ſake, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> life of Ieſu mighte appeare in oure mortall bodies.</p>
               <p>What coulde he haue ſpoken more euident &amp; plaine? For im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly vpon the ſame he ſaith thus: we haue beleeued, therfore
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:10:61"/>
haue we ſpoken, and know, that he, which raiſed vp the Lorde Ieſus, ſhall thorow Ieſus raiſe vs vp alſo.</p>
               <p>Wherefore oure true bodies, which now are mortall, ſhall ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely riſe againe: howbeit after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſurrection, they ſhall no more be mortal but i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mortal. To theſe witneſſes out of gods word, and therfore inuincible, I will nowe alſo adde the teſtimony of Ihon Damaſcene.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Iohannes Demaſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus de or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodoxa fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. Cap. 28.</note>
                  <hi>The Reſurrection (ſayeth he) shall be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, but a true coniunction of ſoule and body, and another laudable reſtitution of it that vvas fallen avvay, and brought to naughte. Therefore the ſame body that pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risheth, is diſſolued and falleth a ſonder and the very ſame riſeth vp againe vndiſſoluble. For he, that in the beginning created man
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:10:61"/>
out of the duſt of the earth, &amp; then brought him againe to earthe and duſte, that he vvas taken of: The ſame (I ſay) is mighty and of povver according to his vvorde, to raiſe vp the ſelfe ſame man againe from death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus much Damaſcenus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And truely euery man nowe may wel thinke, that God, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally for this cauſe, did not cre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ate the firſt man of naughte, as he did other things, but out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> duſt of the earth: that as concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the reſurrection of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, though they turne to duſte and earth againe, we ſhuld haue no doubt. Now, as I ſuppoſe, I haue ſufficiently and plainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the true fleſh of al men, yea euen our own body, and els none for it, yea euen the humain
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:10:62"/>
true body ſhall riſe againe from death: namely formed and faſhio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned with his own right propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, meaſure and property, as a true body: ſo that the meaſure and property of the true bodye, which nowe is deuided &amp; parted in his members and ioyntes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth: that is, he ſhall haue true fleſh, blud, bones, ſynewes, ioynts, members. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 15. The maner hovve the bodies shall riſe againe, and the kinde that they shall be of.</head>
               <p>BVt to the inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay yet be more plainly vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, I wil nowe tel howe oure bodies ſhall riſe, &amp; what nature
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:10:62"/>
and kinde they ſhall be of in the reſurrection. At the ende of the world, ſhall the Lord come with great maieſty vnto iudgement, and ſhall declare and ſhewe him ſelfe, in, and with a righte true eſſenciall body.</p>
               <p>Hether alſo to ſhal he be brou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght &amp; ſhal ſtand in the clouds of heauen, that al fleſh may ſe him. Yea al men that are vpon earth ſhal beholde him, and know him by his glory. In the mean ſeaſon alſo ſhall he ſend his Archangel to blow the trompe. Then ſhall all the dead heare, and perceiue the voice and power of the ſonne of God. And ſo al men, that died from the firſt Adam, ſhal imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:10:63"/>
ariſe out of the earth.</p>
               <p>And al they, that liue vntil the laſt day, ſhall in the twinkling of an eye be changed. And thus all men, euery one in hys owne fleſh, ſhal ſtand before the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te of oure Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, and ſhall wait for the laſt ſentence and iudgement of the Lord: which ſentence, being ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen quicklye and withoute de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay, ſhall call one part into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and thruſt out the other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hell.</p>
               <p>This faſhion and maner of the reſurrection, haue not I imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of my ſelfe, but written it al out of the Euangeliſts &amp; ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the holy Apoſtles. For
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:10:63"/>
thus we reade: The powers of heauen ſhal moue in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt time, and then ſhall appeare the ſigne of the ſonne of man in heauen,<note place="margin">Math. 24.</note> &amp; then ſhall all the kinreds of the earth mourn, &amp; they ſhall ſee the ſonne of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> come in the cloudes of heauen with power &amp; greate glory. And he ſhall ſend his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great voyce of a tro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, &amp; they ſhal gather together his choſen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the foure winds, &amp; from the one end of the world to the other. &amp;c. Herevnto adde, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſpake in Mathewe &amp; Iohn.<note place="margin">Math. 25. Iohn. 5. 1. Theſ. 4.</note> And Paul in the firſt to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalonians, ſaithe: This ſay we vnto you in the word of the lord, that we, which liue &amp; are remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:10:64"/>
in the comming of the lord ſhall not come before the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which ſlepe. For the Lord himſelf ſhall deſcend from heauen w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a ſhout, &amp; the voice of the Archangell, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> trompe of God. And the dead i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt ſhal ariſe firſt. Then ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> we, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> liue &amp; remaine, be caught vp w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them alſo in the clouds, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mete the lord in the ayre. And ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhal we euer be with the Lorde Furthermore to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Corinthian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſaith Paul: behold I ſhew you myſtery.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.</note> We ſhal not all ſleepe but we ſhall all be changed, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that in a moment, in the twin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling of an eye, at the time of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> laſt trompe. For the trompe ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> blowe, and the dead ſhall riſe in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>corruptible,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:10:64"/>
and we ſhalbe chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. For this corruptible muſt put on incorruption, and this mortall muſt put on immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. This is nowe the maner of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſurrection of oure bodies, &amp; in what nature and kind they ſhall riſe againe. But in the reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they ſhall, thorow the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God, be made immortall &amp; incorruptible. For the Apoſtle ſaith expreſly: the dead ſhall riſe againe. After that he ſaithe: this corruptible &amp; mortall, muſt put on incorruption and immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. In the which words y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> terme this, poynteth directly, as wyth a finger, to oure liuing and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine body.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:10:65"/>
                  <note place="margin">Iob. 19.</note>And ſo Iob ſaide: euen I my ſelfe ſhall ſee him, &amp; none other. Wherfore our bodies, after thei be riſen againe from death, ſhall remain euen in their own right ſtate &amp; ſubſtance, as afore. Yea euen y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very ſame men ſhal kepe ſtill theyr nature &amp; kind, as they did afore: ſauing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they, which afore time wer ſubiect to frailti, ſhall from thence forth be pure, clean, perfect, immortal, of a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere and purified nature, ſubiect and obedient vnto the ſpirite.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">VVhat a glorified bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy is.</note>Such bodies, raiſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death, did the olde wryters call glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, purified or glorious bodies, &amp; that according to the doctrine of the holy Apoſtles. Albeit ther
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:10:65"/>
wer ſome which abuſed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> word, and therfore made the veritye of the bodies void &amp; of none effect: beginning to diſpute of glorified bodies, as of the pure ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; eſtate of a ſpirite. Whereof we ſhall ſpeake ſhortly, if God will.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 16. That Paule ſpake rightly of a glorified body, and vvhat a glorified bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is, and vvhat a naturall.</head>
               <p>BVt nowe wil I declare, that Paule did rightly &amp; wel vſe this worde, glorious or glorified body, euen as it is truli in it ſelf. For to the Philippia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s he ſayth: Our dwelling is in heauen, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence we loke for the ſauiour,<note place="margin">Phillip. 3.</note> eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ieſus Chriſt the lord: which ſhall change our vile earthy bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:10:66"/>
that it may be faſhioned like vnto his own glorious body, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the working wherby he is able to ſubdue all things vnto himſelfe. In thys ſentence thou haſte that terme (glorified body) thou haſt alſo of what na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and kinde the glorified bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſhalbe: namely whole, and as the body of Chriſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> roſe againe from death. And thus ſhal it not be a body vtterly made voide, or brought to nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, or altogether turned into a ſprite, &amp; therefore hauing no roume &amp; place, inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible and inuiſible: but it ſhalbe an vprighte very true hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine body, as it is ſufficiently declared afore, where I ſpake of
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:10:66"/>
the true reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the lord. In the which place we vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whan the Lordes diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples thought they had ſene a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rit whan they ſaw the Lorde, he ſaid vnto them: a ſpirit hath not fleſh &amp; bones as ye ſee me haue.<note place="margin">Luke. 24.</note> Handle me and ſee: for it is euen I my ſelfe. The Lord alſo, after his reſurrection, ſet before them ſome faſhion or euidence of hys glorification: namely whan he was tranſfigured before them. And at that time remained the right eſſenciall ſubſtance of the bodye: but in forme and faſhion it was altered, in that it became glorious.</p>
               <p>So ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth it plainly, he was
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:10:67"/>
tranſfigured, and not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was made voyde or broughte to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, or altered into another ſubſtance. Thus ſaith Paule al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo:<note place="margin">Phillip. 3.</note> he ſhall change our body. &amp;c. Wherfore euen the righte true ſubſtance of the glorified bodye ſhall remaine ſtill.</p>
               <p>As for the change or alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it ſhalbe in the infirmities y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> happen vnto vs. So that, whan the body taketh vpon it the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rification and immortality, they ſhalbe wholly remoued and fall away.</p>
               <p>Howbeit, this ſhalbe more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident and plain to vnderſtand, if it be thorow and with dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce conſidered and declared, what
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:10:67"/>
this worde, glory, or glorificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, meaneth.</p>
               <p>For tranſfiguration, glory &amp; glorification, is one thing. So ſaith holy Auguſtin in his boke againſt the Arrians.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To bring to glory, to make glorious, and to glorify, are .iij. vvordes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Contra Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria. cap. 31.</note> 
                  <hi>yet is it but one thing. The Greekes call it doxazein, but the tranſlators in Latine haue othervviſe inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted it. Thus much ſaith Auguſtine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But glory in ſcripture is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for light, brightneſſe and ſhine, as S. Paul ſpeaketh to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians: if the miniſtration, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thorowe the letter killeth &amp; was grauen in ſtone, hathe glory ſo,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.</note> that the children of Iſrael could not beholde the face of Moiſes for the glory of his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenance.
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:10:68"/>
And here vnto ſerueth this ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Daniel: the wiſe, ſuche as haue taught other,<note place="margin">Daniel. 12.</note> ſhall ſhine as the brightnes of heauen: and they that haue inſtructed multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes (or many) vnto godlines, ſhalbe as the ſtarres world with out ende.</p>
               <p>Muche after the ſame wiſe, doth the Lorde himſelfe alſo vſe it, ſaying: then ſhall the rightu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſhine as the Sunne,<note place="margin">Math. 13.</note> in the kingdom of their father. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the glorified bodies ſhall be clere, bright, &amp; ſhining bodies, euen as the body of Chriſt was in his tranſfiguration vpon the Mount of Thabor: of whome it is ſpecified in the goſpell, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hys
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:10:68"/>
face was as bright as the Sun,<note place="margin">Math. 17.</note> and his clothes did ſhine as the light. After the reſurrection, did the lord ſhew vnto his diſciples his palpable and viſible, that is, his very true ſubſtanciall body, but the brightneſſe and ſhine he reſerued, to teache and inſtructe the weake here beneath: like as alſo after the reſurrection he did eate and drinke, not that he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded any ſuche thing, but that he ſo would declare and proue the true reſurrection of his bodye. The glorification alſo is ſet di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly againſt the low eſtate and diſhonor, as Paule euidently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth, ſaying: he ſhal chaunge our vile body, that he may make
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:10:69"/>
it like vnto his owne glorious &amp; glorified body. This worde hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militye, lowe eſtate or diſhonor, comprehendeth all that is called earthy, fraile, miſerable &amp; mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall. For by meanes of our ſins, we are broughte lowe and into miſery: ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we muſt nedes feele &amp; ſuffer ſickneſſe, hunger, thirſt, cold, heat, pain, vexation, mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold luſtes and affections, feare, wrath, heuineſſe, and ſuche like things innumerable, yea, and death alſo at the laſt.</p>
               <p>Againe: glorification compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendeth deliuerance, that is, the laying away &amp; cleare diſcharge of al theſe miſeries and ſorows. So that nowe glorification is
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:10:69"/>
called (and ſo it is in very dede) pureneſſe, perfect ſtrength, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality &amp; ioy: yea a ſure, quiet and euerlaſting life. For Paule ſaith: We, that are in this taber<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nable, ſigh &amp; are greued becauſe we would not be vnclothed:<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.</note> but we woulde be clothed vpon, that mortalitye mighte be ſwalowed vp of life.</p>
               <p>And to the Romains he ſaith thus: I ſuppoſe,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> that the afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of this life are not worthy of the glory which ſhalbe ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vpon vs. For the feruent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of the creature abideth wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for the appearing of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God.</p>
               <p>In all theſe words it is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:10:70"/>
declared, what glorificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on meaneth, and what is vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande by it. Namely a fredome or diſcharge from this fraile ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitude and bondage, and a deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraunce into the gloryous and comfortable libertye of Goddes children.</p>
               <p>By the which fredome, we are deliuered from al ſickeneſſe and frailtye, and from all thraldome of weakneſſe: that is, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all that which bringeth ſickneſſe, heaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and frailty. From all ſuch are we free, diſcharged and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered, hauing now the perfect fruition of god, and made of like ſhape vnto his ſon Ieſus chriſt, as holy ſ. Iohn declareth. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:10:70"/>
ſerueth it well,<note place="margin">1. Iohn. 3.</note> that Paule ſayeth: whan this corruptible hath put on incorruption, &amp; thys mortal hath put on immortaliti,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.</note> then ſhalbe brought to paſſe the ſaying, that is written: death is ſwalowed vp in the victorye.</p>
               <p>Therfore the glorified body, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſignification of glory, ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be a purified bodi, which is pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and clenſed from all frailty and vilenes, and now is clothed vpon and apparelled wyth clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, pureneſſe, ioy and reſt, and finally with the glory of eternal life. That this is now the kinde and nature of the glorified body, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Apoſtle Paul more large<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly and more perfectly declareth
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:10:71"/>
with theſe words: it is ſowen in corruption, and riſeth in incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, and riſeth in incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: it is ſowen in diſhonor, and riſeth in glorye: it is ſowen in weakeneſſe, and riſeth in pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: it is ſowen a naturall bodye, &amp; riſeth a ſpirituall body. Item what he meaneth by the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and by the ſpirituall body, he declareth immediatly vpon the ſame,<note place="margin">A naturall and ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>all body.</note> and ſayth farther: If there be a natural body, ther is alſo a ſpiritual body, as it is wrytten: The firſt ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Adam is made in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a naturall life, &amp; the laſt man Adam into a ſpirituall life. Yet is not the ſpirituall body y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt, but the naturall: and afterward
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:10:71"/>
the ſpiritual. The firſt man is of the earth earthy, the ſecond man is the Lord from heauen. As is the earthy, ſuche are they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are earthy: and as is the heauenly, ſuche are they that be heauenly. And as we haue born the image of the earthy, ſo ſhal we bear al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the image of the heauenlye. This the holy Apoſtle declareth yet more euidently, and ſaithe:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.</note> by one man came death, and by one man commeth the reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the deade. For like as in Adam they all die, ſo in Chriſte ſhal they al reuiue. Thus Paule calleth <hi>Animale corpus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Animale &amp; ſpirituale corpus.</note> the ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh body, which is interpreted y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> natural body, the ſame that hath
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:10:72"/>
his vertue, ſtrength, power, and life of the ſoule: which body we haue of Adam, and it is earthy, fraile and mortal. The ſpiritual body he calleth, not it that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come or made a ſprite: but ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore nameth he the glorified bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy a ſpirituall bodye, becauſe it liueth of the ſprite of Chriſte: which ſpiritual body (that is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible, indiſſoluble and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall) we haue receiued of Chriſt our Lorde. Of all this, is ſufficiently ſpoken in our expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions of the epiſtles of ſ. Paul.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 17. The caſe of oure members in the bodies reſurrection, &amp; of their functio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</head>
               <p>BVt here might ſome ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſai: if our very true bodies with
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:10:72"/>
their members ſhalbe in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, then it foloweth, that the vſe and exerciſe of the members ſhall be in heauen alſo. To this, I geue like anſwere as nowe is ſayde: namely that we ſhall haue euen theſe members and this bodye which we now cary: but ſeeing that thorow y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glorification they ſhalbe made heauenly, they ſhal not neede earthy exerciſe. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhal they vſe any frail thing at all. Heereof commeth it that Paule ſaithe:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.</note> fleſhe and bloude mai not poſſeſſe the kingdom of God, neither mai corruption in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herite vncorruption. By fleſhe &amp; bloude he meaneth not the true eſſenciall body, but bodely fraile
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:10:73"/>
luſtes and tentations whych he now called the earthy and fraile body. Such tentations &amp; luſtes (ſaith he) ſhall not be in the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified bodies, neither ſhall there any fraile bodies be in heauen.</p>
               <p>For he ſaith immediatly vpon the ſame: corruption ſhal not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herite vncorruption, for in the kingdome of God there ſhall be no corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nor frailty. For the heauenly ioy is farre of another kinde and nature, then that it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> receiue or ſuffer ſuche vile &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane luſts and tentations, yea ſuch a ſtained and defiled fleſhe. For afore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodies of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> come in heauen, they muſt be wholely &amp; perfectly altered: that is, clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:10:73"/>
and purified from all filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and frailty.</p>
               <p>This did our ſauioure teache alſo, whan he anſwered to the queſtion of the Saducees,<note place="margin">Math. 22.</note> who denied the Reſurrection of the dead. Of the which I haue writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten much vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpell of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew. Holy Auguſtin ſaith alſo.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This doth ſore hinder the Ethnikes and heretikes, that vve beleeue,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus de fide &amp; ſymbolo. Cap. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>that the earthye bodye is taken vp into Heauen: for they thinke, that into heauen there can come no earthy thing. But they knovv not our ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, neither vnderſtand hovve it is ſpoken of Paule: it is ſovven a naturall bodye, and shall riſe a ſpirituall bodye. For this is not ſpoken to the intent, as thoughe the bodye should become a ſprite, or be changed into a ſprite. For eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> novv alſo our body, vvhich is called naturall (or ſoulishe) and is natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall in deede, is not changed into the ſoule, and become the ſoule. But therefore is the body called a ſpirituall body, that it may ſo
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:10:74"/>
be prepared to dvvell in heauen. VVhich thing commeth to paſſe, vvhan al febleneſſe and earthy blemish is changed into an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly pureneſſe and ſtedfaſtneſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>All theſe are the vvords of Auguſtine.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 18. The diuers errors that ſprong about the article of the bodies reſurrection.</head>
               <p>HEtherto haue I told, what the Scripture of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles doth hold &amp; teſtify concerning the reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the dead, and of our ood<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that is to ſai, our own true fleſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> namely, that our true fleſhe and body ſhall riſe from deathe, and be glorified in the reſurrection, and that the glorification dothe not therfore take away the veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodi, or make it nothing, but dothe tranſlate and bring it
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:10:74"/>
it into a more vprighte and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſtate: ſo that neuertheleſſe the true eſſencial ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the the body remaineth ſtill. Vpon this nowe, to the commodity of the reader, &amp; for a more euident declaration and vnderſtanding of the aforeſaid wordes: I will ſhew what errors ſpring-vp co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the reſurrection of the dead, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any good faithfull Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian may the better auoide the ſame.<note place="margin">Erroures touching the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the flesh.</note> That there haue ben ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, which denyed the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of oure bodies, and had it vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly in deriſion, all Stories de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare. In the which regiſter, the Philoſophers for the moſt parte are reckened and eſtemed them
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:10:75"/>
                  <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Philetus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Philoſop. 2. Timo. 2.</note> of whom Paul maketh mention. In like maner are ther many recited of <hi>Ireneus, Tertullian, Euſebius, Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanius, Philaſtrius &amp; Auguſtine:</hi> namely theſe, the <hi>Simonians, Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentinians, Marcionites, Cerdonians Carpocratians, Caijnes, Archonti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci, Seuerians, Hierarchits, Seleuci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Appellites and Manichees.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Among the Grekes alſo &amp; La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiniſtes there wer excellent me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that turned the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to the gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and yet earthy Hieruſalem, promiſing muche (I wotte not what) of a kingdom of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde to come after the reſurrection: aſcribing vnto vs ſuche bodies, as being partakers of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, ſhould alſo beholden wyth
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:10:75"/>
theſe earthye deſires. To theſe there is fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d yet the third part, which, as touching the ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and ſtate of the glorified bodies, ſo ſaide and taught that they vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly take away and ouerthrew the bodely nature, and gaue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it no more, nor other thing then a ſprite. Againſt the ſecond ſort ſpeaketh holy Hierom: that foraſmuch as they were carnal, they haue alſo loued onely the fleſhe.</p>
               <p>Againſt the third ſpeaketh the ſaide Hierome: that they, being vnthankfull for the benefites of God, would not haue and beare the fleſh, wherin Chriſt yet was borne and roſe againe. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:10:76"/>
he geueth very godly cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, that we tary in the meane way: Namely, that we eſteme and make the glorified bodies no more ſpirituall, then the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectneſſe, property and truthe of the bodies maye permitte and ſuffer.</p>
               <p>Contrarywiſe, that we make them not altogether ſo carnall and vngoſtly, that it myghte he thought, howe that naturall and fraile bodies ſhall be in the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Olde wryters ſay alſo, that Origen did not perfectly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the reſurrection of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſhe,<note place="margin">Origen.</note> but that in the reſurrection he fantaſied and imagined ſuche a body, as hathe little difference
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:10:76"/>
from a ſprite. And therefore in <hi>Definicionibus Ecleſiaſticis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Definici. Eccle. ca. 6</note> there is a Chapter againſte the ſaide Origen, in maner folowing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If that vvhich falleth doe ſtande vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, then shall our flesh truely riſe againe: for the ſame falleth in very deede, and shall not come to nothing as Origenes opinion vvas, that there shoulde be made a shifting and change of the bodies, namely, that there shuld be geuen vs a nevv body for the flesh: but euen the ſame fraile flesh that falleth of the iuſt and vniuſt, shall vvithout febleneſſe riſe againe, that becauſe of ſinne it may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer paine, or els according to his deſertes continue in eternall honor and glory.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 19. The errors of Origen concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the reſurrection, confuted by Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome.</head>
               <p>BVt foraſmuche as I haue once recited Origens opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, touching the reſurrection of
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:10:77"/>
the body, and ſomewhat recited the errors of ſome, that deuided the reſurrection, declaring the ſcornful opinion of thoſe, whom they cal Chiliaſtes: I wil ſhew nowe more largely, what holye Hierome held of the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the dead, and howe he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed the true vprighte beleefe. He ſpeaketh to Pammachius concerning the errors of Ihon biſhop of Hieruſalem: and in the ſame wryting he comprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth the doctrine and opinion of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigen, concerning the reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in maner folowing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Origen ſayth, that in the church there be ſprong vp tvvo errors: the one from vs, the other from the heretikes. Namely that vve, as the ſimple and louers of the flesh, ſay, that
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:10:77"/>
euen theſe bones, this bloud, and this flesh, that is, that oure face, members, and all the proportion of the body,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hieron ad Pamma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chium.</note> 
                  <hi>and the vvhole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy it ſelfe shall riſe againe at the laſt day, ſo that vve shal alſo go vvith the feete, vvorke vvith the hands, ſee vvith the eyes, and hear vvith the eares. This (ſaith he) vve ſpeake as ſimple, homely, groſſe and ignorant people. But the heretikes (as Marcion, Appelles, Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentinus, and madde Manes) deny vvholely and vtterly the reſurrection of the fleshe or body, geuing ſaluation only vnto the ſoule, and ſaying, that oure vvordes are nothing, vvhan vve affirm, that according to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſample and paterne of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt vve shall riſe againe, ſaying that the Lorde himſelfe roſe in a fantaſy or ſprite: and that not onely his reſurrection, but alſo his birth came to paſſe more in imagination, than in very truthe: that is, that he vvas not borne in very dede, but ſuppoſed to be borne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Novve for the opinion and mind of both theſe parties, Origen ſaythe, it pleaſed him not: namely, that he abhorieth the flesh on oure ſide, and the fantaſye on the heretikes part for eche of them doth too muche. And namely they of our ſide, for that they vvold be again, the ſame they vvere afore: and the
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:10:78"/>
other, for that they vtterly denye the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the bodies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And after certain words doth Hierome ſet forth Origens opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and what he held of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, and ſaith.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>There is promiſed vs another body, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, a ſpirituall and heauenly, that can not be comprehended, nor ſene vvith eyes, nor ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing any vvaighte or burthen, and that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the circumſtance and diuerſitye of the places, that it shalbe in, shalbe chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And after certain words doth Hierome ſet forthe the opinion of Origen yet more plainely, ſaying.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O ye ſimple, the reſurrection of our Lord Ieſus Chriſte oughte not to deceiue you, in that he shevved his handes and feete, ſtode on the ſea shore, vvent ouer the fielde vvith Cleophas, and ſaid he had fleshe and bones. This body, that vvas not borne of the ſeede of man, and of luſt or pleaſure of the fleshe, is endued vvith greater fredome then ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:10:78"/>
body, and vvith his nature it is not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like the ſpirituall and heauenly body. For vvhan the dores vvere shut, he entered, and in breaking of the bread, vanished he avvay from their ſight. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But at the laſt,<note place="margin">The confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Origens error.</note> Hierome an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth vnto Origens foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſayth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Like as he shevved his true handes and his true ſides, ſo did he truly eate vvith the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vvent truely vvith Cleophas, ſpake to them truly vvith his mouth, ſate truly at the table vvith them at ſupper, toke the breade vvith his true handes, gaue thankes, brake it and reached it them. And vvheras he immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vanished oute of their ſight, that is aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to the povver of God, and to no fantaſy or falſe body. VVhan he, afore his reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, vvas brought out from Nazareth, that they mighte throvve him dovvne from the top of the hill; he paſſed thorovv the middes of them, that is, he eſcaped oute of theyr handes. May vve then talke vvith Marcion, that his birthe vvas therefore but a fantaſy, becauſe that he againſt nature eſcaped thoſe that had him? Hovve ſayeſt thou, did not they knovve him in the vvay, vvhan he yet
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:10:79"/>
had the body, that he had afore? Vpon this heare the ſcripture: their eies vvere holden, that they should not knovve him. But vvas he any other vvhan they knevve him not, or vvas he any other vvhan they knevve him? Verely he vvas alvvay one and like himſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And therfore, to knovv and not to knovv, is geuen to the eyes, and not to him that is ſene: although it be aſcribed vnto him alſo, that he helde their eyes leaſt they shoulde knovv him. Aftervvard vvith many vvords geueth he anſvver to that, that the Lord en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, vvhan the dores vvere shut. Yet dothe he brefely anſvver thervnto in his Comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries vpon the laſte Chapter of Eſaye, and ſayeth: I maruell that ſome, after Chriſtes Aſcenſion, vvill geue and meaſure him a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy made of the aire, and ſoone returned to aire againe, becauſe the Lord, by the povver of his maieſty, came into the Apoſtles, vvha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es vvere shut, conſidering that afore his reſurrection alſo he vvent vpon the vva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the ſea, permitting the ſame vnto holy Peter: vvho at the firſt, thorovv faith, vval<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vpon the vvater. But aftervvard, vvhan he being fainte in faith, began to ſincke and go vnder, he ſaid vnto him: O thou of little faith, vvhy haſt thou doubted?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="149" facs="tcp:10:79"/>Thus muche wrote Hierome againſt Origen, &amp; many other moe yet in this boke wrytten to Pammachius, againſte Iohn biſhop of Hieruſalem: which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of greatneſſe and lengthe, I haue omitted to put heere in wryting.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 20. S. Hieromes opinion of the reſurrection of the flesh.</head>
               <p>YEt in the ſame booke hathe the ſaide Hierome ſette hys owne opinion, touching the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the fleſh, directing the oration vnto Biſhop Iohn, and ſaying.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If thou vvilt novve confeſſe the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the flesh, after the truthe and not after fantaſy, as thou ſayeſt, then loke, that
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:10:80"/>
vnto the vvordes, vvhich thou haſte ſpoken to content the ſimple, that euen in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, vvherin vve die and are buried, vve shall riſe againe, thou adde theſe vvords alſo, and ſay: ſeeing the ſprite hathe not fleshe and bones, as ye ſee me haue: and foraſmuch as it vvas ſo diſtinctly ſpoken vnto Thomas: put thy finger in my hands, and thy hand in my ſide, and be not faithleſſe but beleuing: Therefore ſaye thou, that vve alſo after the reſurrection shall haue euen the ſame mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, that vve daily vſe, yea euen the very ſame fleshe, bloude, and bone. The vvorkes vvherof the holy ſcripture condemneth and reiecteth, and not their nature.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And this is the right and true knovvled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of the reſurrection, vvhich ſo geueth honor vnto the flesh, that therevvith it mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisheth nothing the verity of the fleshe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Afterwarde ſpeaketh he yet more euidently.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I vvil frely confeſſe, though ye vvry your mouthes at it, ſcratch your head, and ſcrape vvith your feete, yea, and though ye should ſtone me to deathe forthvvith: Yet vvill I manifeſtly and plainly knovvledge and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the faithe of the church or congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God, and boldly pronounce that the
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:10:80"/>
right profound Chriſtian truth of the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, can vtterly not be vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out flesh, bone, bloud and members.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhere flesh, bones, bloud, and members are, ther muſt nedes be a difference of kind, as of man and vvoman. And vvhere theſe bothe are diſtincte the one from the other, there Iohn muſt be Iohn, and Mary muſt be Mary. But thou nedeſt not to be aſtonied at the matter, as though a vvedding alſo vvere there to be kept in all the haſte: ſeeing that before they died, they liued vvithoute the vvorke of their kinde, that is, vvithoute the acte of mariage.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is promiſed vs, that vve shalbe like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Angels, that is, partakers of the ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: in the vvhich ſaluation, the Angels are vvithout fleshe and diſtinction of kind. And yet it is geuen vnto vs in our flesh &amp; kinde. Thus beleueth my ſimplicity, and vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth that the kind muſt be vnderſtand, hovv be it vvithout the vvorks of the kinde: yea that men muſte riſe againe, and ſo become like vnto the Angels of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Neither oughte the reſurrection of mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers forthvvith to be therfore eſteemed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable &amp; ſuperfluous becauſe they shall not do their office, but ſtand idle. For vvhile vvee are yet in this life, vvee endeuor oure
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:10:81"/>
ſelues not to performe the vvorkes of oure members. As for the compariſon tovvardes the Angels, it is not a changing of men into Angels, but it is an increaſing of the morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus much haue I ſpoken of the confeſſion of holy Hierome.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 21. S. Auguſtines minde of the Reſurrection of the fleshe.</head>
               <p>TOuching the reſurrection of oure fleſhe, not onely did holy Hierome beleue thus, who yet teſtifieth, that he knowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſeth the vniuerſall Chriſtian faithe: But alſo S. Auſten wholely agreeth vnto ſ. Hierome, and namely <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractat. Cap.</hi> 3. For in repeting &amp; correcting certaine poyntes out of the .32. Chapter in the booke
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:10:81"/>
                  <hi>de Agone Chriſtiano,</hi> he ſayth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I ſayd it shall not be flesh and bloud, but an heauenly body. This oughte no man to vnderſtand, that therefore there shall be no true ſubſtance of the fleshe: but vvith the names of fleshe and bloud, muſt the infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the fleshe and bloud be vnderſtand.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Item. Lib. 1. Retractat. cap. 17.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In repeting and correcting cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine poyntes, whych he had wrytten long afore, in the booke</hi> de fide &amp; ſymbolo: In the time of the Angelical chaunge <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> it shal not be fleshe and bloude, but onlye a body. &amp;c. This I ſpake of the changing of earthye bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies into heauenly. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But if one vvold vnderſtand it ſo, that the earthy body, vvhich vve novv haue, should ſo in the reſurrection be altered and chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, that theſe members and the ſubſtance of this fleshe shall not remaine, no doubt he is not in the right vvay, but ought better to be inſtructed: conſidering that he is vvar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and monished thorovve the bodye of oure Lord, vvhich after the reſurrection ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared euen vvith the ſame members, not
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:10:82"/>
only that he mighte be ſeene vvith eyes, but handled alſo and touched vvith handes.</p>
               <p>Beſides this, he teſtifieth, that he hathe true fleshe vpon him, vvhan he ſaythe: han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle me and ſee, for a ſpirit hath not flesh and bones as ye ſe me haue. Therfore it is euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and plain that the holy Apoſtle Paul denied not, that the true ſubſtaunce of the fleshe should not be in the kingdome of God. But rather vvith theſe vvords, fleshe and bloud, he vnderſtode, that either men, vvhich liue after the fleshe, should not haue the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of heauen: or elſe that there shoulde be in heauen no infirmity of the flesh at all. This is a greeuous matter for vnbeleuers, and hardly are they perſuaded to beleue the reſurrection: but moſte diligently and after my povver, haue I treated thereof in the laſt boke de Ciuitate Dei.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">De ciuitate dei. Lib. 13. ca. 22. &amp;. 23.</note>
                  <hi>Yet handleth he of the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not only in the laſt boke, but alſo in the</hi> .13. <hi>boke</hi> de Ciui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Dei <hi>he wryteth thus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Chriſtian faithe doubteth verely no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all, to confeſſe of our ſauioure, that alſo after the reſurrection, though novve in the ſpiritual fleshe, yet alſo in his true flesh,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:10:82"/>
he did eate and drinke vvith his diſciples. Hereof are they called alſo ſpiritual-bodies: not that they therefore ceaſe to be bodies, but that thorovve the ſpirite, vvhich geueth life, they shalbe preſerued and remaine.</p>
               <p>For like as theſe our bodies, vvhich haue a liuing ſoule,<note place="margin">And the ſame is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. Retractat. Li. 1. cap. 13</note> and yet be not named a ſpirite that geueth life, but naturall or ſoulishe bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and therfore are not ſoules but bodies: ſo shall the glorified bodies be called ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall.</p>
               <p>Yet God forbid vve shoulde therfore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that they shall be ſpirites: but bodies shall they be, vvhich shall haue the ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the flesh. And foraſmuch as they are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued and made aliue thorovve, the ſpirite, they shall ſuffer no greefe or infirmitye. Then shal not man be ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thy, but heauenly: not that the bodye, vvhich is made of the earthe shall no more continue the ſame bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: but that thorovv the heauenly gift and grace he shall be ſo from henceforthe, that being ſuch a kinde and nature as can not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishe, and altered from all infirmity, he shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be able to dvvell commodiouſly in heauen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Furthermore ſaith ſ. Auſten in the.</hi> 22. <hi>boke the</hi> 30. <hi>Chapter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hovv the bodies there shall moue, I dare
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:10:83"/>
not rashly define for I can not comprehend it, it paſſeth my vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding. Yet shal their mou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng and ſtate, euen as alſo their propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, be altogether beutifull: and hovv ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it shall be, it shall be in that place, vvher nothing can be but that, vvhich is beutifull and comely: yea vvhere the ſprite vvil, there ſtraight sha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l the body be alſo. Nether vvill the ſpirite any thing that is not very ſemely and comely bothe for him and it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus haue I hetherto recited ſ. Auguſtins beleefe, to conclude this matter of the reſurrection.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 22. VVhat Aurelius Prudencius thought of the ſame.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>J</hi> Will herevnto adde the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the excellent and chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian man, Aurelius Prudenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, which do wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derfully expres vnto vs the reſurrection of oure fleſhe, and ſet it directly before our eyes.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="157" facs="tcp:10:83"/>
                  <l>MY body in Chriſt shall riſe againe:</l>
                  <l>I ſpeake it earneſt for it is plaine.</l>
                  <l>VVhy vvould thou then I should deſpaire,</l>
                  <l>O flesh, vvhan I do ſee ſo faire</l>
                  <l>The vvay, that Ieſus Chriſt, my Lord,</l>
                  <l>VVent after his death, as ſaith his vvorde?</l>
                  <l>This is the ground, and foundation,</l>
                  <l>My heart beleeueth vvith confeſſion:</l>
                  <l>That I am ſure, and knovve certaine,</l>
                  <l>My body shall riſe vvholely againe.</l>
                  <l>Not one heer leſſe, then vvas before:</l>
                  <l>Neither in greatneſſe any more:</l>
                  <l>VVith ſtrength and shape as it liued here,</l>
                  <l>Afore they it to graue did beare.</l>
                  <l>There is no tothe nor naile ſo ſmall,</l>
                  <l>No heer ſo litle, but though it fall:</l>
                  <l>Yet perishe it shall not finally,</l>
                  <l>But out of graue riſe certainly.</l>
                  <l>God vvhich afore created me,</l>
                  <l>VVith shape and ſtrength vndoubtedly,</l>
                  <l>VVhervvith I here on earth should liue:</l>
                  <l>No feble nor vveake thing me shall geue.</l>
                  <l>For vvhere any thing shall perishe at all,<note place="margin">Our bodies at the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on shal not be feeble nor vveake.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>It is olde feble. So do not thou call,</l>
                  <l>Of our bodies the renouation.</l>
                  <l>Therfore is this my expectation.</l>
                  <l>VVhat ſickneſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> paine and aduerſity,</l>
                  <l>VVhat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ale of miſery,</l>
                  <l>Out of this vvorld <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>vve taketh avvay:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="158" facs="tcp:10:84"/>Shall, vvhan I riſe at the laſt day</l>
                  <l>From death to life a nevv, certaine</l>
                  <l>be geuen me all together againe.</l>
                  <l>For ſeeing that death is ouercome:</l>
                  <l>It euer beſemeth vs all and ſome,</l>
                  <l>Quietly to truſt, vvith ſtedfaſtneſſe:</l>
                  <l>Our God vvill kepe vvith vs promeſſe.</l>
                  <l>Leaſt vvhan vve come into the graue,</l>
                  <l>A man no hope then after haue,</l>
                  <l>VVhan he to life commeth eternall,</l>
                  <l>That he, for his body mortall,</l>
                  <l>VVhich here ſo full of faultes vvas,</l>
                  <l>As brickle and fraile, as any glas,</l>
                  <l>Shall haue a body of perfectneſſe,</l>
                  <l>That colde can not, nor hunger preſſe.</l>
                  <l>Though vveakneſſe be, at all ſeaſon,</l>
                  <l>The ſtrength of death, and operation.</l>
                  <l>Therby in vs vvhat is conſumed,</l>
                  <l>VVhan it againe shalbe reſtored.</l>
                  <l>Then thorovv the povver, vvherby vve riſe,</l>
                  <l>VVe go to the father in perfect vviſe.</l>
                  <l>This should right vvell content our hart:</l>
                  <l>Therfore my body regardeth no ſmart.</l>
                  <l>In Chriſt my truſt, is conſtantly:</l>
                  <l>VVho promiſeth vs aſſuredly,</l>
                  <l>To ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe vs vp from earth at laſt:</l>
                  <l>Therfore be thou nothing agaſt.</l>
                  <l>For ſickneſſe nor for aduerſitee:</l>
                  <l>Nor yet let thou the graue feare thee.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="159" facs="tcp:10:84"/>Let this euer thy comfort be,</l>
                  <l>That Chriſt prepared the vvay for thee,</l>
                  <l>VVherin himſelfe is gone before.</l>
                  <l>Folovve thou and liue for euermore.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 23. The bodies of vnbeleeuers shall verely riſe againe.</head>
               <p>BVt to the intent that no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doubt, touching the reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of the fleſhe of the vnbele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers: I will bring forth certaine teſtimonies of holy Scripture, which doe manifeſtly declare, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the vnbeleuers or vngodly, ſhall with their own true bodies riſe againe.<note place="margin">Eſay. 66.</note> The Prophet Eſay in the laſte Chapter of his booke ſayeth: they ſhall goe forth, and loke vpon the bodies of them, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue vilely behaued themſelues
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:10:85"/>
againſte me: for their wormes ſhall not die, neither ſhall theyr fier be quenched, &amp; all fleſhe ſhal abhorre them. With this ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence doth the Prophet play af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the maner &amp; cuſtome of thoſe that haue ſone gotten the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: which with great deſire, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that the battaile is won, get them out of the city into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> field, to viewe &amp; loke vpon the bodies of ſuche as are ſlaine, and howe fortunately they haue foughte. Foraſmuch nowe as Chriſt alſo hath foughte proſperouſly, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come his ennemies on domes daye, and made them his foote ſtole: the faithfull ſhall go out to ſee the bodies of the vngodlye.
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:10:85"/>
The prophet doth for this cauſe call them bodies, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to declare, that the bodies, raiſed vp from deathe, ſhall be very true fleſhe. He continueth further alſo in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> recited ſentence, and ſaith: their worme ſhall not die. For the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies or coarſes are full of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, neither are they aught but wormes meate.</p>
               <p>Al this is ſpoken after the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome and property of man, and weaknes of this time: and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyth is deſcribed vnto vs, and ſet before our eyes, eternall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, and howe it ſhall goe in the life to come.</p>
               <p>In Daniel we read thus:<note place="margin">Daniel. 12.</note> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them, that ſlepe in the duſt
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:10:86"/>
of the earth, ſhal awake: ſome to euerlaſting life, ſome to perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſhame &amp; reprofe. The whole multitude of bodies, ſayth he, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are become duſt, yea al fleſh ſhal thorowe the power of God riſe againe, but not in like caſe and ſorte. For the good ſhall ariſe to eternall life, the euill to euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting death. After this manner ſpake the Lord alſo: verely, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely,<note place="margin">Iohn. 5.</note> verely I ſay vnto you: The houre commeth, in the which all they, that are in the graues, ſhal heare his voice, and ſhall come forth: they that haue don good, to life: and they that haue done euill, to deathe. Who is ſo igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rante but he perceiueth, that to
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:10:86"/>
ſlepe in the erth, as the prophet Daniell ſayde, and to be in the graues, as Chriſte ſaide, is one maner of ſpeche and of like ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect? Now foraſmuch as they, that are in the duſt of the earth, and in the graues, come forth, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake and riſe againe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and onely the bodies are in the graues, wherin they corrupt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it foloweth that mens true bodies, not only of the good, but alſo of the euill, ſhall truely riſe againe. And the ſame doth the Lord yet declare more euidently. Mat. 10. Feare ye not them, that kil the body, &amp; are not able to kil the ſoule: but rather feare him, which may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy ſoule and body into hell.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="164" facs="tcp:10:87"/>Not only the ſoules, but alſo the bodies of vnbeleuers, dothe the Lorde deſtroye. Oute of the which it foloweth, that they ſhal riſe againe: for if they ſhould not riſe againe, they coulde not be tormented and plaged. Neither ſhall any other body riſe againe to paine and puniſhment, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the ſame, that with his vſe works hath deſerued the plage.</p>
               <p>And herevnto ſerueth alſo the deſcription of the laſt iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Math. 25. And S. Paule ſayth. 2. Cor. 5. We muſte all appeare before the iudgement ſeate of Chriſte: that euery one may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue in his bodye, according as he hath don, whether it be good
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:10:87"/>
or bad. See, how manifeſtly &amp; expreſly the holy Apoſtle teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the body ſhall riſe again. In the ſame terrible iudgement of God ſaith he, muſt euery one take his body to him again. And why muſt he take the body vpon him againe? Euen to the intent, that wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any one hath receiued his body again, he may likewiſe receiue the rewarde, that he by and with his liuing body hathe deſerued.</p>
               <p>Nowe hathe the bodye ſome thing to do with godlineſſe and vngodlineſſe, with vertue and vice: for the body is an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or veſſell wherwith ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what is done: and therfore in the
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:10:88"/>
iuſt iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God, the body, according to the deuine righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, ſhal not be omitted, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther forgotten at all.</p>
               <p>For if it haue bene obedient and ſubiect vnto the ſpirite, if it haue ſuffered muche trouble for the name of Ieſus Chriſte, if it hath bene an earneſt folower of rightuouſneſſe: then ſhall it bee worthy alſo to be glorified. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: If it hathe bene geuen o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to worldly voluptuous plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, or tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſitory things of this world: then with the ſoule that wrought with it, ſhal it iuſtly go to eternall damnation. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the vnbeleuers ſhall truely riſe againe in their owne fleſhe:
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:10:88"/>
yea eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ſame, which they heere in this time haue fed, and pampered wyth all voluptuous pleaſure and exceſſe.</p>
               <p>And like as they in this time haue with their body take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their owne pleaſure, ioy and delight: ſo in the life to come they ſhalbe plaged and puniſhed with euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting pain and torment, in the ſame body.</p>
               <p>For S. Paule witneſſeth far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the acts of the Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Actes. 24.</note> and ſayeth: I worſhip the God of my fathers, beleuing al thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs which are written in the lawe &amp; in the prophets: and haue hope towards God, that the ſame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the dead, which they
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:10:89"/>
themſelues looke for, ſhall be of the iuſt and vniuſt.</p>
               <p>Therefore holy Auguſtine in boke <hi>De fide ad Petrum diaconum</hi> ſaid wel and Chriſtianly,<note place="margin">De fide ad Petrum. cap. 3.</note> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the nature of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles doctrine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The vnrighteous shall haue a common reſurrect on of the fleshe vvith the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: but the grace of the change, or glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, they shall not haue. For frailty and miſery shall not be taken avvaye from the bodies of the vngodly, neither the shame and reproch, ſickneſſe and febleneſſe, in the vvhich they are ſovven: vvhich therefore thorovve deathe are not extincte and taken avvaye, that they maye belong to eternall death, paine and punishment, euerlaſtingly to be plaged body and ſoule, vvith continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all torment that neuer ceaſſeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe are Auguſtines vvordes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And after like ſorte did the lord alſo ſay in the goſpel: they,
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:10:89"/>
that haue done euil,<note place="margin">Iohn. 5.</note> ſhall ariſe to the reſurrection of iudgement or damnation. As if he would ſay: the vngodly, that with their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies ſhall riſe againe, ſhall riſe with ſuch property and propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theyr bodi, that theyr bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies maye ſuffer the paine and torment: namely, that they now being made euerlaſting, maye not be waſted and conſumed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way thorow any paine or trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, how great and horrible ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it be. And ſo the bodyes of the vngodly, that riſe againe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death, ſhall after the ſaid maner be altered and changed. For the bodies that might afore thorow pain and trouble be broken and
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:10:90"/>
conſumed, are nowe altogether as yron, yea ſuche as can not be broken, and yet painful and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible: ſo that from henceforthe, the more they be tormented, the harder thei become, and, thorow Gods vengeance, more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apte to be deſtroyed, and yet made the more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſuffer mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="part">
            <pb n="171" facs="tcp:10:90"/>
            <head>
               <hi>¶The thirde parte</hi> TOVCHING THE damneds perdition and the bleſſeds ſaluation.</head>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 24. The deathe and damnation of the vngodly.</head>
               <p>NOwe ſeeing the onſet is geuen, and the Oration come ſo farre, that I muſte alſo ſpeake ſomewhat of the eternall death and damnation of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleuers, that this matter maye be wholely, vprightlye, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly brought to an end: I will therfore brefely declare, that the
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:10:91"/>
death, and damnation of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleuers and vngodly, is enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto them of God. Item, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſoules are paſſible. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer wher the ſcripture declareth the place of damnation to be, &amp; after what ſort damnation ſhall torment the vnbeleuers. Final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I wil declare, whether the pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſhment of the vngodly be euer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>laſting, or whether it ſhall ceaſe at lengthe. Holy ſcripture dothe oft and many times make men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the deathe of the ſoule,<note place="margin">The death of the ſoul.</note> which yet co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerneth not the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, but the ſtate thereof.</p>
               <p>For holy Auguſtine in his boke <hi>de fide &amp; ſymbolo,</hi> ſpeaketh ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of very wel and Chriſtianly.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="173" facs="tcp:10:91"/>
                  <hi>Like as the ſoule</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of vices and vvicked maners is fraile,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De fide &amp; ſymbolo. cap. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>ſo may it alſo be called mortall. For the deathe of the ſoule, is to fall from God, and not to keepe it ſelfe vnto God: vvhich is alſo the firſt ſinne committed in paradiſe, as it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined in holy ſcripture.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moreouer the ſoule dieth, vvhan it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely ſpoiled of eternall life, and caſte into e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting ſorovve, trouble, and miſerye.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And therfore, ſaythe Auguſtine farther. <hi>The ſoule alſo hathe her deathe, Namely vvhan it lacketh and is deſtitute of the eternall and godly life; vvhich truly and iuſtly is called the life of the ſoule. But vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deadly or immortall is it called, becauſe it neuer ceaſeth to liue, hovve miſerable ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the life of it be.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What bodely death is, euery man knoweth well: but eternall death, whan a man dieth the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time, is this: when the fleſh riſeth again, and ſo is placed in euerlaſting torment.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="174" facs="tcp:10:92"/>For after the laſte ſentence or iudgement of God, the whole man, and not the halfe, ſhall be either ſaued or damned. The e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall death alſo hath S. Iohn in his Reuelation called the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond death.<note place="margin">Apo. 2.20.</note> This is appoynted becauſe of ſinne, and is not a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting or ceaſſing, but a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuall paine. This death is called alſo damnation, that is, a iudgement bicauſe the vngodly is adiudged vnto paine: and for that there is appoynted him a torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſorow and trouble that neuer ceaſeth, and that, as touching the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe therof, can neuer be expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with tonge.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <pb n="175" facs="tcp:10:92"/>
               <head>CHAP. 25. That ther is an eternal death and damnation, and that the ſoule is paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible.</head>
               <p>NOw that there is an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal damnation, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truthe and righteouſneſſe of God teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth. For howe coulde God be rightuous, if he had no puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, wherwith to torment and plage the vicious and wicked? Therfore out of dout an eternal deathe and damnation there is, though the vngodly do mocke &amp; laughe it to ſcorne, and paſſe not vpon it. The godly ſacred Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, which is an aſſured witneſſe of the truthe, ſayeth euidently: death is the ſtipend or rewarde of ſinne. And:<note place="margin">Rom. 6.</note> by one man came ſinne into the worlde,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.</note> and by ſin
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:10:93"/>
death. Item, thorow the ſinne of one man, is the euil fallen by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, &amp; come vpon all men vnto damnation. For, in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> boke of Geneſis,<note place="margin">Gene. 3.</note> God ſayth: In what day ſo euer thou eateſt of thys tree, thou ſhalt die the deathe.</p>
               <p>Now did he eate therof, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he alſo died, and was euen condemned, appoynted and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudged vnto eternall death. The Lord ſayth alſo in the goſpel:<note place="margin">Iohn. 8.</note> if ye beleue not that it is I, ye ſhal die in your ſinnes. Item: he, that beleeueth not,<note place="margin">Iohn. 3.</note> is condemned al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redy. Such like teſtimonies are found in holy ſcriprure innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable: out of the which we final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conclude, that death &amp; damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:10:93"/>
is enioyned, appoynted and adiudged of God, vnto all vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuers and vngodly. But foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muche as there be ſome whiche thinke, that, ſeing the ſoule is a ſprite, it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not, neither may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, yea that it is not ſubdued to any paſſion at all: Therfore, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch curious teachers, I wil ſet now the ſoule of the gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious riche man in the goſpell, which expreſly &amp; plainly ſayeth: O ſende Lazarus, that he maye dipe the tip of his finger in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and cole my tunge:<note place="margin">Luke. 16.</note> for I am tormented in this flame: lo, the rich mannes ſoule is tormented in the fire. Hereout now it folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth, that the ſoules are paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:10:94"/>
and ſubiect to ſuffer.</p>
               <p>And thoughe this be ſhewed vnto vs of the Lorde as a para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, yet is it done for this inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, euen to deſcribe and declare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs the ſtate and caſe of the ſoules, that are ſeperated from the bodies.</p>
               <p>And how pain and puniſhment is appoynted vnto the ſoules, it is fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d expreſſed not only in the ſimilitudes, but alſo in the holye goſpell of Mathewe the truthe it ſelfe ſaythe: feare ye hym ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which may deſtroy ſoule &amp; body into hell.</p>
               <p>What the mouth of god ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, muſt nedes be true: Yea a ſhamefull &amp; ſtrange thing were
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:10:94"/>
it: for any man from henceforth to doubte in this, that with ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident teſtimonies is witneſſed.</p>
               <p>We ought rather to beware, that wyth oure vicious life, we deſerue not to learne and fele by experience, the righteous iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, concerning the which we nowe doubte and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde ſo foliſhlye, as thoughe there ſhalbe nothing of it. Now what I haue ſpoken of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoules, that are already departed from the body, muſt be vnderſtand al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of the bodies, whych come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to the ſoules in the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 26. The bodies of the vnbeleuers, being raiſed, are paſſible.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb n="180" facs="tcp:10:95"/>FOr that the bodyes, whych come againe to the ſoules &amp; are raiſed vp, are paſſible: it mai well be vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d and perceiued by that, which is treated of alre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. S. Auguſtine <hi>Lib.</hi> 21. <hi>de ciui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Dei. Cap.</hi> 4. ſheweth by many naturall examples and euiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that liuing bodies may wel remaine &amp; continue in the fire. But touching the place of the puniſhment, or where the ſoules with their bodies ſhalbe tormen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted, the ſcripture ſaithe ſimply &amp; plainly, that the vnbeleuers goe downe into hell. Hereof is it ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy to perceiue, that hell is vnder vs in the earth: notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding to go about to deſcribe, to ſhewe
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:10:95"/>
and to compaſſe preciſely the place and the rowme, where it lieth, and to poynt it out, becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not vs verelye, but is a fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhe preſumption. The teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the ſcripture are ſimple &amp; plaine.<note place="margin">Pſal. 55.</note> For the Prophet Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid ſaythe: let death fall ſodenly vpon them, &amp; let them go downe quicke into hell: for wickedneſſe is in their houſes and priuye chambers. Item: with all theyr ſubſtance went they down quick into hell,<note place="margin">Nume. 16.</note> and the earthe couered them, and they periſhed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oute of the congregation.<note place="margin">Gene. 19.</note> Heerevnto ſerueth alſo righte well the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of Sodome, and that whiche the Prophet Ezechiell
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:10:96"/>
declareth:<note place="margin">Ezech. 32.</note> namely, that all cruel people are gone downe and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded into hel: as the Elamites, which are the Perſians, Edo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites, and others. And therfore concludeth he farther, that euen Pharao, the king of Egipte, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he alſo is a tyrant, muſt be thruſt downe into hell, and be gathered vnto other vncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, that is to ſay, vnbeleuers. Item in Luke is the hell placed beneath downewards.<note place="margin">Luke. 16.</note> For thus is it wrytten in the Euangeliſt: betweene vs and you, there is a greate ſpace ſette: ſo that they, which woulde goe downe from hence to you, can not.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">1. Peter. 2.</note>The holy Apoſtle Peter ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:10:96"/>
of the angels that fel, ſaith euidently: that they are caſte downe into hel, kept and bounde with the chaines of darknes for euer. Eſay alſo ſpeaketh of hell,<note place="margin">Eſay. 30.</note> and ſayeth: the Lord hath ſet hel in the deepe, and made it wide. As for the manner, faſhion, and meaſure of the damnation, and how great y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of hel is vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vnbeleuers: I ſuppoſe no to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g is able to expreſſe the terrible &amp; vgſome paine and puniſhmente therof. For Virgile the old Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ete, though he were an Heathen man,<note place="margin">Virgilius.</note> yet wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had recited di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers and ſondry vices, and what puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is ordeined for them of God, he ſaid in his ſixte boke
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:10:97"/>
of the Eneydes.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>An hundred tunges,</l>
                  <l>And mouthes as many,</l>
                  <l>Although I had,</l>
                  <l>VVith eloquence hie:</l>
                  <l>And though my voice</l>
                  <l>All yron vvere</l>
                  <l>In ſtrength: yet coulde</l>
                  <l>I not declare</l>
                  <l>The vices of men,</l>
                  <l>Nor yet can tell,</l>
                  <l>VVhat paines therfore</l>
                  <l>They ſuffer in hell.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="97" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 27. The paines of Hell, and the matter for the continuance of the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, vvith the ſpace of the place, and kindes of punishments.</head>
               <p>YEa thoughe the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it ſelfe, can not with ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient words expres the paines of hel, and puniſhment of the da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: yet dothe it partly deſcribe the ſame with outward and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:10:97"/>
things, geuing vs occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereby, to conſider far grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter things: and, ſo to ſay, oute of the ſmall to ponder and wey the greater: as whan it calleth the paines of hel, the outward dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, that is, moſt terrible ſorow &amp; trouble, calling the paine alſo weping and gnaſhing of teethe. Item, colde: and continuall fier that neuer quencheth, &amp; the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall gnawing worme. As e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one that hathe red the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, is well enformed. The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Ezechiel ſayth,<note place="margin">Eze, 32.</note> that in hell there is a greate multitude of graues. And ſo, by a figuratiue &amp; borowed ſpeache, he declareth the horror, mourning, weeping,
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:10:98"/>
and lamentation of the damned. The Grekes in their language named hell of darkneſſe, colde, trembling and quaking.</p>
               <p>For <hi>Ades</hi> commeth of, <hi>a,</hi> and <hi>Eidein,</hi> that is of not ſeeing: or <hi>Tartarus</hi> of the word <hi>tartarizeia.</hi> that is, to ſhudder for cold: or of <hi>taratto:</hi> that is, to be in heuines, put in fear, and out of quiet. But for the opening of this matter, we will take the teſtimonies of the ſcripture in hand againe.</p>
               <p>The Lord ſayth: at the end of the world, ſhall the ſonne of man ſend forthe his angels, and they ſhall gather out of his kingdom all things that offend, and them which do iniquitie, and ſhal caſt
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:10:98"/>
them into the fier ouen: there ſhalbe wailing and gnaſhing of teethe. And euen the ſaid words doth the Lord vſe againe in the ſame Euangeliſt.<note place="margin">Mat. 22.24.</note> Item Eſay ſayeth:<note place="margin">Eſay. 30.</note> for he from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning hathe prepared Tophet, that is, hell euen for kings, and made it depe and wide.</p>
               <p>The manſions or chambers therof are of fier and exceading muche woode, which the breath of the Lorde, as a riuer of brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, dothe kinde. The place of the Prophet haue I partly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, in the expoſition of the .5. chapter of Mathewe, and heere will I now partly expound it.</p>
               <p>The prophet truly, with theſe
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:10:99"/>
words, declareth an aſſured and a very wide and broade place of hell, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaith: he hath made it depe and wide.</p>
               <p>Hereof than it foloweth, that hell is in the depth, and that the place it ſelf is an horrible depth, ſo that who ſo dothe once ſincke down into it, ſhall come no more thereout: nether nedeth any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to thinke, that the place is not great and wide inough. For tou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ching wideneſſe, it ſhall be able inough to holde all damned per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
               <p>For, the wideneſſe and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe therof, ſayth the Prophet, is exceading horrible. The ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible pain alſo &amp; torment, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyth
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:10:99"/>
the vngodly are puniſhed, hath the prophet deſcribed with theſe words, and ſayd: the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions or chambers therof are of fire. As if he wold ſay. The pain of hell is greater then can be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, for the fire noteth an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>outſpeakeable trouble. As for ſtuffe to be tormented withal, it ſhal neuer lacke, neither ſhal the paine haue euer any end. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſayth he, that there is much woode. It foloweth moreouer, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Lords breath, which is as a riuer of brimſton, doth kindle, and as a belowes, blow the fire, quickning it, and euer renuing it, to burne euermore. Therfore we ought not to thinke that that
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:10:100"/>
fire is kept in bi natural cauſes: for by the power of God is it kindled and kepte in. The ſame Prophet ſayth alſo: they ſhal go forthe and loke vpon the bodies or coarſes of them,<note place="margin">Eſay. 66.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue vilely behaued the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues againſte me: for their wormes ſhall not die, neither ſhall their fire be quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, and all fleſhe ſhall abhorre the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And vnto theſe words hathe the Lord reſpect, whan he ſayth in the goſpell of Marke: better is it for thee to goe halt or lame into life,<note place="margin">Marke. 9.</note> then hauing two fete to be caſt into hell, into the fire that neuer ſhall be quenched: where their worme neuer dieth, &amp; their fire neuer goeth out.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="191" facs="tcp:10:100"/>Herein therfore conſiſteth the puniſhment and da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation, that the vngodly, which heere vpon earth wolde not know God, and receiue the lighte of the goſpell, ſhall be caſt out from the face of God, wherin only yet is the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and perfectneſſe of all ioy: and than ſhall they be ſhut vp in the great, thicke, and perpetuall darkneſſe. For the iudge com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth them to depart from him, and to go into eternal pain and damnation. Yea the vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhall go into themſelues, and ſhal know y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> equity of the iudge: and therfore fret &amp; gnawe theyr owne heart, with ſighing, wyth vnſpeakeable pain, great ſorow
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:10:101"/>
and trouble.</p>
               <p>This is called, and ſo it is in dede, the gnawing worme, that in the hartes of the vngodly ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer dyeth. For S. Paule ſaythe plainli,<note place="margin">Rom. 2,</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> at the righteous iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of God, the conſciences of all men ſhall beare witneſſe, and that the thoughts in themſelues ſhall either accuſe or excuſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <p>The ſame S. Paul alſo, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the iudgement of God, ſaith: praiſe, honor and immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitye ſhall he geue vnto them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue in good doing, and ſeeke eternall life: but vnto them, that are rebellious, diſobeying the truth, and folowe iniquity, ſhall come indignation &amp; wrath, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:10:101"/>
&amp; anguiſhe. Beſides all this, ſhal the vngodly be in the felow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of moſte foule ſprites, wyth whom they had their luſt in this life.</p>
               <p>There ſhall all be full of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, lothſomneſſe, and greate torment, and ſo ſhal all burne to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether for euermore. For thus ſhall the iudge geue ſentence w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> plaine and expreſſe wordes: de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part fro me ye curſed, into euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting fire,<note place="margin">Math. 25.</note> which is prepared for the deuil and his Angels.</p>
               <p>The Prophet Daniel ſayeth alſo: the wicked ſhal riſe to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall ſhame and rebuke. Item Eſay: all fleſh ſhall abhor them. And holy ſcripture ſayeth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:10:102"/>
vngodly are geuen ouer vnto y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> deuill, to burne perpetually.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 28. The Refutation of them, that denied the punishment of the vngodly to be eternall.</head>
               <p>MOreouer ſ. Auguſtin ſaith in the laſt boke <hi>de ciuitate Dei. That ſome heeretofore haue beene ſo mercifull, that they durſt promiſe grace, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance and life, euen vnto thoſe that are damned and adiudged to eternall death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame witneſſeth alſo S. Hierome, in his wryting vppon the laſt chapter of Eſay.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But no man ought to be moued by ſuche a folishe and erronious opinion of certaine vnbeleeuers: vvhich opinion hathe of all faithfull men beene euer ſtill reiected and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned. For the teſtimonies or vvitneſſe of the ſcriptures, vvhich vvholely vvithoute all contradiction are to be credited, ſpeake ſimply and plainly, that the punishment and damnation of the vngodly or vnbeleuers is euerlaſting, and not onely of long continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:10:102"/>
as ſome expound it: but ſo great, that it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be expreſſed, and ſo perpetual, that it is vvithout end.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Herevpon, for the opening of the matter, we will ſhew mo te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies. Eſay ſaythe: thy ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers ſhall become rozine,<note place="margin">Eſay. 34.</note> &amp; the duſt brimſtone, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth burning pitche, not able to be quenched day nor night: the ſmoke ſhall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally go vp, from generation to generation ſhal there be a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: neither ſhall any man be able to walke there in euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting eternity.</p>
               <p>The Prophet doubtles ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of hel, minding with many wordes to declare, that the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment and paine of hell is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall and without end.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="196" facs="tcp:10:103"/>For firſte he ſayeth: day and night ſhall it not quenche. Then ſayeth he farther: the ſmoke ſhal goe vp ſtill for euermore. Item, yet more plainly: from generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to generation ſhall there be a deſtruction: namely a dwelling, where as is nothing but paine and vndoing.</p>
               <p>And at the end he addeth: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhal any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be able to walk there, in the euerlaſting eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Which is ſuche a manner of ſpeache, that ſcarce there can be any other founde, that more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly, euidently and plainely expreſſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eternity. For what is the euerlaſting eternity elſe, but a time withoute ende? But
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:10:103"/>
to be able to dwel or walk ther, ſignifieth not, that no man ſhall dwel in hel: but that it is a loth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome horrible place, wherin eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man deſireth neither to dwell nor walke.</p>
               <p>Other Prophetes alſo, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the deſtruction of lands and Cities, haue with ſuche like maner of ſpeche, deſcribed a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry foul and horrible ſubuerſion. Therfore woulde the holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Eſay alſo expreſſe here no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, but an euerlaſtyng lothſomnes, that neuer ceaſſeth. In the holy Prophet Daniel, it is wrytten thus: they,<note place="margin">Daniel. 16.</note> that haue inſtructed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> multitude vnto god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe,
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:10:104"/>
ſhall ſhine as the ſtarres in <hi>ſeculum &amp; in perpetuum,</hi> for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and euer.</p>
               <p>Now leaſt that by this word, <hi>ſeculum,</hi> any man vnderſtande a long ſeaſon, as an hundreth, a thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d or .10000. yeres, he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth therevnto immediatlye <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perpetuum,</hi> that is, in to the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, or for euermore. And like as the eternity is appoynted for the rightuous, ſo is there an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting eternity ordeined for the wicked. For the Lord ſaythe plainly. They y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue don good, ſhal come forthe to the reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of life: and they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue done euil,<note place="margin">Iohn. 5.</note> to the reſurrection of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:10:104"/>
Note here the manner of ſpeche, to the reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of life, and to the reſurrection of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Nowe haue I ſhewed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that this ſaying, to riſe vp vnto the reſurrection of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is aſmuche as to riſe to a continual &amp; ſtil remaining ſtate, in the which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodies raiſed vp endure perpetually in torment. We finde alſo the like in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame goſpell of Iohn, that the Lorde ſaythe: who ſo beleeueth on the ſonne, hathe eternall life: but he that beleueth not the ſonne,<note place="margin">Iohn. 3.</note> ſhall not ſee life, but the wrath of god abideth vpon him. Loe, what could be more euidently and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thely ſpoken? He ſhall not ſee
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:10:105"/>
life, ſayth the Lorde. Item: the wrathe of God remaineth vpon him. If he ſhall not ſee life, howe ſhal he then, as yonder men ſay, be preſerued or ſaued? Item: If the wrathe of God abide vppon him, then ſurely the vengeance, that is, the paine &amp; puniſhment, ſhall not be taken away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him. And note, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſaith: the wrathe of God abideth, yea abideth on him. As if he would ſay: the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth vpon him, ſtic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth faſt, moueth not away, alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not, but worketh in the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleuers without ceaſſing for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore. The Lord ſaythe: all ſinnes ſhall be forgeuen the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Marke. 3.</note> and alſo the blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:10:105"/>
wherwith thei blaſpheme. But who ſo blaſphemeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Ghoſt, hathe no forgeueneſſe for euermore, but is gilty of eternal iudgement. For euermore, ſaith he, hath he no remiſſion.</p>
               <p>And herevnto he addeth: he is in da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger of eternall iudgement, that is, he ſhalbe puniſhed wyth euerlaſting continuall puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The lord ſayth moreouer in the ſame Euangeliſte:<note place="margin">Marke. 9.</note> better it is for thee, to enter into lyfe halte or lame, then hauing two fete, to be caſt into hell fire: the fire that neuer quencheth, wher their worme dieth not, &amp; theyr fire goeth not oute. Wherein he repeateth once againe, that the
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:10:106"/>
fire neuer quencheth, and addeth therto, that the worme neuer di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. Wherfore as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodies euer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue, ſo endureth their worm alſo perpetually. For the worme liueth and is ſuſteined onely of the body or caryon. S. Iohn al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſayth in his reuelation:<note place="margin">Apo. 14.</note> if any man worſhip the beaſt and hys image, and receiue his mark in his forehead, or on his hand: the ſame ſhall drinke the wine of the wrathe of God, which is poured in the cup of his wrathe. And he ſhall be puniſhed in fire &amp; brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, before the holy Angels &amp; before the Lambe. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſmoke of theyr tormente aſcendeth vp for euermore, and they haue no
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:10:106"/>
reſt day nor night. &amp;c. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like is repeated in the .20. Chapter. Thus muche of eternal damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 29. Of eternal life and ſaluation, and that there is an eternall life.</head>
               <p>NOwe reſteth, that in the end of this boke we col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect ſomewhat oute of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning euerlaſting life, and the moſte perfect ſaluation of all elect, which is our only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and only hope, that we vndoubtedly looke for and truſt to inherite, and that thorow the benefite and merits of our Lord Ieſus Chriſte. That there is a bleſſed and eternall life, no man ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deny, vnleſſe he be altogether
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:10:107"/>
an enemy of god, &amp; except there be in him no life at all. For if there be no euerlaſting life, and no euerlaſting ſaluation, then is there alſo no God: or thoughe there were one, yet were he nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther true nor iuſt, ſeing that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all rightuous and faithfull he hath promiſed eternall life. But a God there is, who is true and rightuous: therfore is there alſo an eternall life &amp; ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which he hath promiſed to faithfull be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuers. This doth holi ſcripture recorde with theſe witneſſes. Dauid ſaith:<note place="margin">Pſalme. 27.</note> I beleue and truſt to ſee the richeſſe of the Lorde. And in the goſpel the lord ſaith:<note place="margin">Math. 25.</note> Come ye bleſſed of my father, &amp;
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:10:107"/>
poſſeſſe the kingdome, whyche hath ben prepared for you from the beginning of the worlde. I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, O thou good and faithfull ſeruaunt: thou haſt bene faithfull in a litle, I will make thee ruler ouer much: enter into the ioy of thy Lord. Paule alſo ſaith: if we haue a ſure hope in Chriſte Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus only in this life,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15. Heb. 4.</note> then are we of all people the moſt wretched. And with many wordes to the Hebrues treateth he of the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting reſt.</p>
               <p>But in the .11.<note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> chapter he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of the hope of the faithfull: They deſire a better countrey, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, an heauenly. Item He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brues .13. we haue heere no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:10:108"/>
citye, but we ſeeke one for to come. For holy ſcripture calleth eternal life the kingdom of God, the kingdome of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the natiue countrye of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, the ioy of the Lord, the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed reſt, and euerlaſting life. S. Peter ſpeaketh very euidently and plaine:<note place="margin">1. Peter. 1.</note> praiſed be God, the father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt which, according to his aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant mercy, hath begotten vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine vnto a liuely hope by the reſurrection of Ieſus Chriſte from deathe, to an inheritance immortall and vndefiled &amp; that periſheth not, reſerued in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for you, which are kepte by the power of God thorow faith vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſaluation. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="chapter">
               <pb n="207" facs="tcp:10:108"/>
               <head>CHAP. 30. VVhere the place of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full is.</head>
               <p>YEt are there ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me, that aſke where the region or place of the bleſſed and faithful beleuers is. Of this haue all rightuous &amp; godly men had euer one opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: namely, that the dwelling of the liuing ſhall be with God, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that, whiche the Lorde ſayth in the goſpell:<note place="margin">Math. 5.</note> bleſſed are they which be of a pure hart, for they ſhall ſee God. And though God be euery where, yet will he not be ſene in this time, but prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cipally in the time to come, and in heauen, according as Moſes hath wrytten,<note place="margin">Exo. 33.</note> no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhalbe able to ſee God &amp; liue. Therefore is
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:10:109"/>
it neceſſary for vs to depart oute of this time, and to be broughte elſewhere: namely to the place y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is aboue vs, where God dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in a lighte,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.</note> that no man can atteine vnto, as Paul ſaith. For there wil he be perfectly ſene of his. In S. Luke it is red, that Abrahams lappe, or boſome, is aboue in the heigth: but the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borow or dwelling of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> damned beneth in the depth. It is found alſo,<note place="margin">4. Reg. 2.</note> that Helias was in a firie charet taken he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and caried vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards into heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And in Iohn doth oure Lorde Ieſus Chriſte pray,<note place="margin">Iohn. 17.</note> ſaying: father, thoſe whom thou haſt geuen me, I will that, where I am, they alſo be there
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:10:109"/>
with me, that they mai ſee mine honor and glory. But in this, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I haue treated of afore, it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly declared, that the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is the ſame rowme and place of Ieſus Chriſt, into the which he is bodely taken vp in his glory. Wherof then it foloweth of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, that the heauen, into the which Chriſt aſcended wyth his true body, is eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame place and reſt, that faithfull beleuers are taken vp into.</p>
               <p>And into the ſame heauen de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired Steuen to be receiued, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he lifte vp his eyes into heauen, and ſaw at the right hand of the father Ieſus ſtanding, to whom he committed his ſoul, and ſaid:
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:10:110"/>
O Lord Ieſu receiue my ſpirit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 31. Hovve the ſaluation shall be.</head>
               <p>BVt what the ſame life, and of what ſorte, faſhion and maner the ſaluation of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſhalbe, or what the elect doe or occupy in heauen, can of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal men not perfectly be ſpoken. For ſ. Auguſtine alſo in his .22. boke <hi>de ciuitate Dei. cap.</hi> 29. ſaith.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">De ciuitate dei. Lib 22. cap. 29.</note>
                  <hi>If I vvill ſay the truth, I can not tell after vvhat manner the operation, reſt and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the bleſſed in heauen shall be. For the peace of God excelleth and paſſeth all mannes vnderſtanding.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And likewiſe ſpeaketh alſo ſ. Paule out of the Prophet, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the quality,<note place="margin">Eſay. 64. 1. Cor. 2</note> faſhion and manner of eternall life: the eye
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:10:110"/>
hath not ſene, and the eare hath not heard, neither haue entered into the hart of man the things, which God hathe prepared for them, that loue him. Wherefore touching the excellency of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life though all were ſpoken that the tongs of men wer able, yet ſhould it be hard for them to attain, and by words to expreſſe the leaſte and ſmalleſt portion thereof.</p>
               <p>For albeit we heare, that the kingdom of Chriſt be filled with glory, ioy, and ſaluation, yet the things that are named, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue ſtill farre from oure vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: yea they remaine wrapte, as it were, in a dark ſpeche and
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:10:111"/>
in a miſte, vntill the daye come wherein he will open and geue vnto vs his glorye. Therefore whan the holy Prophets coulde with no wordes expreſſe the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall ſaluation, as it is in it ſelfe: yet as much, as was poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, they deſcribed &amp; ſet it forthe by outward and bodely things. Therefore we maye alſo, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, by outward and corporall things gette vp, as it were by ſteppes, to things inuiſible, and purchaſe vnto our ſelues an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of ſpirituall &amp; euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting goud things. For S. Paule to the Romanes, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the knowledge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true onely, and eternall God, ſaythe,
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:10:111"/>
y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Gods inuiſible things, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly his eternall power and god-heade, are vnderſtande,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.</note> if hys workes be pondred and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. And oute of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> good things, that here vpon earthe are geuen vnto men, hathe the Poet Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellus very goodly and wel con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded and compted, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the good things, which for the bleſſed are prepared in the life to come, ſhal be ſuche, as now can not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered and expreſſed. And thus he ſaythe.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>O</hi> Heauen, that art the throne moſt hie,<note place="margin">Marcellus de piſcibus</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>A beautifull crovvn, faire &amp; vvorthy,</l>
                  <l>Hovve vvonderfull, pure and excellent,</l>
                  <l>Art thou beſet in firmament,</l>
                  <l>VVith ſtarres, vvith ſun, and mone doutles,</l>
                  <l>Replete vvith ioy and much gladnes:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="214" facs="tcp:10:112"/>VVhich God for vs hath prepared,</l>
                  <l>And cattell to geue hath not ſpared,</l>
                  <l>VVaters and vvoode, vvith many a hill,</l>
                  <l>vineyardes, medovves, faire fields to till.</l>
                  <l>Pleaſant on earth and commodious:</l>
                  <l>Thy dvvelling, O Lord, hovve precious</l>
                  <l>Is it? All full of honor and glory</l>
                  <l>For thy celeſtiall hoſt vvith thee.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Moreouer holy ſcripture ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth very ſimply and plainely, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> eternall life conſiſteth here in, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhall ſee God, and haue the fruition of him, in whome is the fulneſſe of al good, and wythout whom nothing can be deſired or found, that is good, beautifull or pleaſant. For eternall life or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal ſaluation is nothing elſe, but mannes euerlaſting and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way continuing ſtate, which by meanes of the beſt things of all,
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:10:112"/>
is fully perfect.</p>
               <p>This ſtate is geuen vs, thorow the beholding or ſighte, thorowe the fruition and thorowe the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion or felowſhip, whych we ſhall haue wyth the bleſſed God in the world to come.</p>
               <p>Hereof is it that S. Aug. ſaith <hi>Lib.</hi> 22. <hi>De ciuitate Dei cap.</hi> 29.<note place="margin">De ciuitate dei lib. 22. cap. 29.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If I be demaunded, vvhat the bleſſed shal do in this ſpirituall body, I shall not ſay that I novve ſee but that vvhich I beleue. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſay, that euen in this bodye they shall ſee God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus alſo did holy Iob holde therof, and ſayd:<note place="margin">Iob. 19.</note> I ſhall ſee him to my ſelfe, and mine owne eyes ſhall ſee him, yea I and none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Euen of this occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpake S. Auguſtine in the laſt chapter
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:10:113"/>
of this .22. boke, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> corporall eyes of the body raiſed vp,<note place="margin">Lib. 22. cap. Vlt.</note> ſhall execute their office, that is, they ſhall ſee. What he farther trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the beholding of god, it is penned at large in the .112. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle,<note place="margin">Epiſt. 112. ad Paulin. Iohn. 17.</note> which he wrote <hi>ad Pauli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam.</hi> Our Lord Ieſus ſaith alſo in the holy goſpell: this is the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life, that they know thee to be the only true, God, &amp; who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e thou haſte ſent Ieſus Chriſte. This knowledge is not only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe, and the knowledge of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding: but alſo the preſent beholding and fruition of God, and the fellowſhip wyth God, which after this life ſhall happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto all faithfull beleuers. For
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:10:113"/>
Paule ſaid: we ſee now thorow a glaſſe in a darke ſpeaking,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.</note> but then face to face. For faithe is a ſtedfaſt ſubſtance of things, that we hope for, and as a beholding or ſight of God: albeit ſomwhat more darke, and not ſo euident &amp; cleare, as ſhall be that, whych, as a reward of faith, ſhall be ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the faithfull in the worlde to come. To ſee face to face is nothing elſe but to vſe, enioy, &amp; haue the fruition of all things: preſently alſo to behold the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe, and perfectly to be perta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker therof. Therefore ſayeth the holy Apoſtle Iohn yet more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidently: dearly beloued,<note place="margin">1. Iohn. 3.</note> we are now the children of god, and yet
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:10:114"/>
it dothe not appeare what we ſhall be: but we know, that whan he ſhall appeare, we ſhall be like him: for we ſhal ſee him as he is. With the which wordes ſ. Iohn will declare three things: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that euen nowe in this verye preſent time we are Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and therefore alſo heyres. And though this be a great fore deale and an excellent iewel, yet the great and vnſpeakeable glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that in time to come ſhall be declared vnto vs, hathe not yet appeared. For we, ſaith he, ſhall be like him, namely oure Lorde Ieſu Chriſte: who, according to the ſaying of Paule, ſhall alter and chaunge our frail body, that
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:10:114"/>
he maye make it like vnto hys owne glorified body.</p>
               <p>Beſides this, euen as he is, ſhall we ſee him: namely Chriſt the Lord, not onely as man, but alſo as very God. Therfore ſhal we ſee god as he is: namely god as the onely cheefe and higheſt good, in whom we haue al good things. For Paule ſayth:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.</note> whan all things are ſubdued vnto the ſonne, then ſhal the ſonne alſo be ſubiect vnto him, who vnto him hath ſubdued all things, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God may be all in all.</p>
               <p>And therefore ſayde he alſo in the goſpel:<note place="margin">Iohn. 17.</note> that they know thee to be the onely true God. Not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt is not very god, but that
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:10:115"/>
the myſterie and the intreating of the ſonne, oure mediator &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciler, ſhal after the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t be no more ſo in heauen, as it hath ben afore vpon earth. But the only God, in the holy Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſhall be of all good the full perfecte ſufficiencie to all faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. For all that we can wiſhe, thinke, and deſire, ſhall only god geue and be in all things.</p>
               <p>And that is alſo the meaning and vnderſtanding of Paule, whan he ſayth:<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Cor. 15.</note> God ſhalbe all in all. And heerevnto ſerueth nowe the goodly ſentence of S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine,<note place="margin">De ciuitat. Dei lib. 22. cap. 30.</note> who ſayth thus: God ſhall be the end of al our longing and deſire: him ſhal we perpetually
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:10:115"/>
ſee, him ſhall we loue wythoute tediouſneſſe and grefe, and hym ſhal we praiſe wythout ceaſing. For tediouſneſſe and grefe run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth cuſtomably with ſaturati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or fulneſſe. As for vs, we ſhal with the beholding of God, be filled to the bodelye ſatiſfying: which filling ſhalbe as little te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious or greuous, as we are gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued at the waters and riuers, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſtil run into the ſea, and yet oute of the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of the earthe ſpring forth againe.</p>
               <p>For the ſame co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to paſſe withoute all mens tediouſneſſe, yea rather wyth great ioye and commodity, ſeing they water &amp; moiſture all things, and make
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:10:116"/>
the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fruteful. And herevnto ſerue now theſe teſtimonies of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture: the Prophet Dauid ſayth: in thy preſence is the fulneſſe of ioy,<note place="margin">Pſalme. 16.</note> and at thy righthand there is pleaſure for euermore: that is in the beholding of thee, is, and conſiſteth all ioy, and in heauen ſhall euerlaſting pleaſure be.</p>
               <p>Item: in thy rightuouſneſſe ſhal I behold thy face:<note place="margin">Pſalme. 17.</note> and whan I awake, I ſhall with thy like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe be ſatiſfied. Vnto the Lord alſo ſayth the holy Apoſtle Phil lip:<note place="margin">Iohn. 14.</note> Lorde ſhewe vs the father, and it ſuffiſeth vs.</p>
               <p>Therfore the Poete Marcel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, ſpake very Chriſtianly and well in theſe his verſes.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="223" facs="tcp:10:116"/>
                  <l>HEreof hath God his name truely,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe the higheſt good is he.</l>
                  <l>For vvhere he is, there is preſent</l>
                  <l>Much honor and glory excellent.</l>
                  <l>And therfore euery pleaſant thing,</l>
                  <l>That vvater and earth dothe heere forthe bring,</l>
                  <l>And vvhat in the aire is beautifull,</l>
                  <l>That may delite and be frutefull:</l>
                  <l>There is in all that number not one,</l>
                  <l>VVhich is not ſeene at all ſeaſon,</l>
                  <l>VVithin the circle of heauen ivvis:</l>
                  <l>VVhere the higheſt fathers dvvelling is.</l>
               </q>
               <p>The bleſſed alſo and elect, ſhal in the heauenly and eternal cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, with continuall praiſe inceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly, laude and magnifye the name of God.</p>
               <p>For whan ſ. Iohn in his reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation thought to ſignify &amp; ſhew this, he ſayd:<note place="margin">Apo. 5.14.</note> I hard the voice of many angels, which wer about the throne and about the beaſts
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:10:117"/>
and the elders. And I heard ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny thouſands, that ſang a newe ſong, ſaying: worthy is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lambe, that was killed, to receiue pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and richeſſe, wiſedome and ſtrength, honor, glory, and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. &amp;c. Moreouer the ſame e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life ſhalbe altogether fre and diſcharged from all heaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſickneſſe and temptatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, wheras temporall ioy, reſt, and welfare of men is mixt with ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe. As alſo the holye Apoſtle Iohn dothe witneſſe: I Iohn, ſayth he, ſawe that holye Citie, new Hieruſalem, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming down from God out of heauen, prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as a bride garniſhed for her huſbande. And I harde a great
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:10:117"/>
voyce out of heauen, ſaying: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde the tabernacle of God is with men, and he wil dwel with them, and they ſhall be his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and God him ſelfe ſhalbe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them, and ſhalbe their god. And God ſhall wipe away all teares from theyr eyes. And there ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be no more death, nether ſorow, nether crying, nether ſhal there be any more paine: for the olde things are gone. And he, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſate vpon the ſeate, ſayd: Beholde, I make all things newe. And he ſayde vnto me: wryte, for theſe wordes are faithfull &amp; true. And herevnto in manner ſerueth all, that followeth after in the .21. chapter to the ende of the boke.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="chapter">
               <pb n="226" facs="tcp:10:118"/>
               <head>CHAP. 32. The ſoules departed, vvotte not vvhat they do that are aliue, thereby any thing to be diſquieted.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">De cura pro mortu. is agenda. cap. 13.</note>
                  <hi>THerfore did holy Auguſtin alſo teach, that the ſoules of thoſe, that are departed, wotte not what they doe, which are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue. Yet wil I reſite his words. Thus ſayth Auguſtine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If the ſoules of thoſe, that are departed, vvere among the doings of ſuche as are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue, they shoulde, vvhan vve ſee them in ſleepe, talke vvith vs: and then, I vvill not ſpeake of others, at the leaſt my good and faithfull mother, that by vvater and lande folovved me ſo farre, to be vvith me, should novve not forſake me. For God forbid, that he shoulde haue made that bleſſed life more vnfrendly or more terrible.</p>
               <p>God forbid, that vvhan my hearte dothe any thing preſſe and vnquiet me, she should not comfort me her ſonne, vvhome shee yet ſo entierly loued, that shee could neuer ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer or ſee me heauye. Vndoubtedly it muſte needes be true that the holy Pſalmiſt ſayth:
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:10:118"/>
my father and my mother haue forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me,<note place="margin">Pſal 27</note> but the Lord hathe taken the cure to keepe me. If our fathers novve and mothers haue forſaken vs, hovve can they be then in oure cares and doings? And if father and mother do nothing at all in our buſineſſe, hovv can vve then thinke, that the other dead medle ought vvith vs,<note place="margin">Eſay. 63.</note> or knovve vvhat vve doe or ſuffer. The Prophet Eſay ſayth: thou O God, art our father: for Abraham vvotteth not of vs, and Iſrael knovveth vs not.</p>
               <p>Seing then that ſuch honorable Patriarks vviſt not, vvhat vvas don concerning their people, vvhich came of them ſelues, to vvho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yet, as to Gods faithfull beleeuers, the ſame people vvas promiſed oute of their ovvne ſtocke: hovve can then the dead open them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues the dore, to knovve and further the doings and not doings of them that are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue? And hovve shall vve be able to ſaye, that they, vvhich are dead, vver helped and eaſed, afore the euill came that folovved vp on their death: vvhan they after death fele all the calamity and miſerye of mannes life, that here happeneth vnto vs? Or be vve in erroure, that ſpeake ſuch things, and compt them to be in reſt? Or doth he erre, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the vnquiet vvay of the liuing ſo care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and full of combrance? I praye thee,
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:10:119"/>
vvhat great benefite is it then, that our lord God promiſed the vertuous king Ioſias: namely that he should die, becauſe he shuld not ſee the great miſery,<note place="margin">4. Reg. 22.</note> vvhich god threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto all the land and people of Iſraell? The vvoordes of the Lorde vnto Ioſias are theſe: Thus ſaithe the Lord God of Iſraell: ſeeing that by reaſon of my vvordes, vvhich thou haſte heard, thy heart hath melted, and thou haſt humbled thy ſelfe before the lord, vvhan thou hardeſt vvhat I had threatned vnto this place and to the inhabiters there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, namely hovve they shalbe deſtroyed, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute and accurſed, and thou there vpon haſt rent thy garment and vvept before my ſight: Beholde I haue heard thee, ſaythe the Lorde God of hoſtes. The plage shall not touche thee. Beholde, I vvil gather thee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy fathers, &amp; into thy graue shalt thou be laid in peace: and thine eyes shall not ſo all the plages, that I vvill bring vpon thys land, and vpon thoſe that dvvel therein. Lo, this king, ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding in avve at the threatning of God, did vvepe and rent his clothes: and thorovve death, that came afore hand vvas he in ſafety from all miſery to come. For he muſte afore departe in peace, and take reſt, leaſte he shoulde ſee that greate calamitye. Therfore the ſoules of thoſe, that are depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:10:119"/>
muſte needes be in ſuche a place, vvhere they ſee not all that is done, and happeneth in the life of men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>All this haue we taken and wrytten out of the .13. Chapter of Auguſtines booke</hi> de cura pro mortuis agenda.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If the ſoules nowe in euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting ſaluation haue a perfecte reſt, yea ſuche a reſt as their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, which they haue put of, hath not yet receiued againe: and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that they are yet aliue, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſpecially loued, while they were with them in body: howe much more perfect ioy ſhal they then firſt haue and poſſeſſe, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr bodies ſhall come againe, and whan they ſhal ſee, that all their brethren, whome they in
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:10:120"/>
this life had loued ſo intirely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, are together in honor and glory, whan now y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hath ceaſed, and whan in the eternall time there can nowe no cauſe of heauineſſe and grefe be thoughte vpon, nor founde anye more at all. Therefore the glory and ioy, which the mercy of god ſhall after the laſte iudgemente geue vnto menne, that are made whole againe of body and ſoule, ſhalbe wythout ſorow, and in all poyntes perfect. And like as the vngodly, and vnbeleuers, ſhalbe gathered together with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill and all his companions: ſo ſhall alſo the rightuous &amp; electe haue the ioyfull fruition of the
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:10:120"/>
company and felowſhip of their head Ieſus Chriſte, and of hys members, that is, of all faithfull beleuers.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 33. The faithfull shall knovv one an other in heauen.</head>
               <p>THen alſo ſhall the bleſſed knowe one another again, hauing ioy together, and reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in the obtained health. For if there ſhuld be no knowledge, to what ende then ſhould the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies riſe againe? Or what frute and profit ſhould the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on haue? Or how might the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Daniel the Prophet be verified, whan he ſaith:<note place="margin">Dan. 12.</note> they that haue inſtructed &amp; taughte other
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:10:121"/>
vnto godlineſſe, ſhall ſhine and be as light, as the ſtarres in the firmament?</p>
               <p>Whan the Lord was riſen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain from death, and hath taken vpon him his glorified body: the Apoſtles knew him, yea ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly and thorowly well knewe they him, that, as S. Iohn wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth, none durſt ſay: who art thou? For they all knew, that it was the Lord. I paſſe ouer, that the Lorde ſpake in the goſpell, ſaying:<note place="margin">Luke. 22.</note> whan the ſonne of man ſhall ſit vpon the ſeat of his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, then ſhall ye alſo ſit vpon 12. ſeats, &amp; iudge the .12. tribes of Iſrael.</p>
               <p>For if they, that riſe againe,
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:10:121"/>
ſhall not know one another, how ſhall then the Apoſtles iudge &amp; geue ſentence vppon thoſe, to whome they preached heere in theyr life time? Note, that the Apoſtles ſhall iudge in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> roume and place of their lord, to whom only is geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all power to iudge: but this vnderſtanding it hathe, that the apoſtles do then iudge, whan they are there at the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall court, as witneſſes of the rightuous iudgement of God, wyth the which he condemneth the vnbeleuers.</p>
               <p>For where as the vnbeleuers woulde not geue credence to the Apoſtles, that is to ſaye, theyr preachers, but cried oute vpon
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:10:122"/>
the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as vpon vngodly heretikes: whan they nowe ſhall ſee thoſe preſent w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the iudge of all men, they ſhall immediatly be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by the Apoſtles, and haue witnes in themſelues, that they ſhalbe and are iuſtly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned. And for this matter read the .4. and .5. Chapter of the Booke of Wiſedome, which ſerueth very well to this purpoſe. And ſeeing it is manifeſt, that, in the life to come, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the wicked ſhal know the good, howe much more then ſhal one good perſon know ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and one faithfull another. In the Tranſfiguration of the Lord vpon the mount appeared Moſes and Helias, and were
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:10:122"/>
knowen of the three diſciples of the Lorde:<note place="margin">Math. 17.</note> yea they knewe the Lord himſelfe, thoughe he was nowe tranſfigured.</p>
               <p>Herevnto ſerueth it alſo, that Paule ſaith:<note place="margin">Heb. 12.</note> ye are come to the city of the liuing God, the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtial Ieruſalem, and to an innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable multitude of Angels, and to the congregation of the firſte borne ſonnes, whiche are wrytten in heauen, and to the ſprites of the perfecte rightu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. &amp;c. Beſides thys, we haue for vs the vniforme and vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal opinion of all faithful, which alſo witneſſeth, that in the life to come, the bleſſed ſhall knowe one another.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="236" facs="tcp:10:123"/>For whan we talke of deathe, and of the ſtate and caſe of the life to come, we ſay: though we nowe muſt departe a ſonder, yet ſhall we ſee one another againe in the eternall country.</p>
               <p>Socrates alſo, the righte fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and moſt excellent among all the wiſe men of the heathen, marked ſuch a like thing, &amp; ſawe it as in a dreame, whan, as Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero witneſſeth of him,<note place="margin">In tuſcula queſti.</note> he was vnto death condemned of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges or counſel, and nowe ſhould drinke the poyſon. For he ſayd: O howe muche better and more bleſſed is it, to goe vnto them, that well and vprightlye liued here in time, then to remaine
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:10:123"/>
here in this life vpon earthe? O howe deare and worthy a thing is it, that I may talke wyth Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheus, Muſeus, Homerus, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiodus, with thoſe excellent me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Verely I woulde not onely die once, but manye &amp; ſondry times alſo, if it were poſſible, to obtain the ſame. &amp;c. After this ſort, like as in a dreame, did the good Philoſopher imagine in himſelf ioyes vaine and of none effecte. But we promes vnto our ſelues true aſſured ioy, in that we hope and knowe, that in the eternall and euer during countrye, after the oeſurrection of the dead, we ſhall ſee Adam, our firſte father:<note place="margin">Adam. Noe.</note> Noe, the dearly beloued frende
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:10:124"/>
of God:<note place="margin">Abraham.</note> Abraham, to whom god made ſpeciall greate promiſes: Moſes,<note place="margin">Moyſes.</note> the moſt gentle hearted man, and one, that had greateſt experience of all the myſteries of god:<note place="margin">Samuel.</note> Samuel, the frendly and louing prophet: Dauid, the king and Prophet,<note place="margin">Dauid.</note> who was Gods elect according to his owne wil and deſire:<note place="margin">Ioſias.</note> Ioſias the moſt god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and beſt among all the kings of Iuda: likewiſe Iohn y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſte,<note place="margin">Iohn Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt.</note> holyer then whome there was none borne of woman: and with all theſe, the holy Virgine Mary,<note place="margin">Mary.</note> the mother of God, and highly repleniſhed wyth grace among all wemen.</p>
               <p>Item, Peter, Iohn, Iames,
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:10:124"/>
chefeſt of the Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Peter. Iohn. Iames. Paule.</note> with the other diſciples of Chriſt: Paul, the famous teacher of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, and all the holy congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Patriarks, Prophets, Apoſtles, Martirs and faithfull beleuers.</p>
               <p>As for our glorified and pure vnderſtanding &amp; memory, nowe endued wyth immortalitye, the multitude and infinite number of the bleſſed, in our ſaid natiue country, ſhall nether greeue nor entangle the ſame.</p>
               <p>From the beginning of the creation, there was in Adam a wonderfull and excellent effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce, foraſmuche as vnto all
<pb n="240" facs="tcp:10:125"/>
things, and to euery one in eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall, what ſo euer was wythin the whole compaſſe of the world created, yea in paradiſe alſo, he gaue theyr names, and knew e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one.</p>
               <p>A muche more excellent, more pure and more cleare vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſhall God geue to the rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vp and glorified bodies: ſo that they ſhall not lacke, nor be deſtitute of any thing at all.</p>
               <p>And where as the bleſſed ſhal reioyce and haue ioye together one wyth another, yet ſhall all their delight be in the only god, who ſhall be all in all. Of theſe euerlaſting &amp; heauenly things, more &amp; farther to wryte, I haue
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:10:125"/>
not at this preſent.</p>
               <p>How be it there ſhalbe graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly geuen vs things far grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, muche more glorious, more ioyfull and more diuine, then we can comprehend, namely, ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as it is in it ſelfe, in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> daye, whan we, after the ouerco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming and treading downe of deathe, thorow our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, ſhall be caried vp and taken to heauen, into eternal ioy and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. Touching the whych, I haue hetherto wrytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Maieſty and worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thereof, but after my ſmall ability in moſt humble wiſe.</p>
               <p>God the father of all mercye, thorowe hys deare ſonne oure
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:10:126"/>
Lord &amp; redemer, Ieſus Chriſte, vouchſafe graciouſly to take vs pore ſinners vp to his glorye, &amp; after the ioyfull reſurrection of oure body, that we long for, to geue &amp; ſhew vs the vnoutſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ioy, which he hathe prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for all faithfull beleuers: that we euer liuing, and hauing ioy in him, maye prayſe him for euer &amp; euer, that is from eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to eternity. So be it.</p>
               <p>With Chriſt, euen in death, is life.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:10:126"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A TABLE of the Chapters</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TEINED IN THIS Booke, and heere folovveth the chapters of the firſt part.</head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <list>
                  <label>CHAP. 1.</label>
                  <item>The authors purpoſe 1.</item>
                  <label>CHAP. 2.</label>
                  <item>The Lord verely roſe vvith his body. 3</item>
                  <label>CHAP. 3.</label>
                  <item>Appearings of the body raiſed vp. 14</item>
                  <label>CHAP. 4.</label>
                  <item>The body of Chriſte roſe again, not a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit but a tru body. 16</item>
                  <label>CHAP. 5.</label>
                  <item>The frute of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of Chriſt. 23.</item>
                  <label>CHAP. 6.</label>
                  <item>Of the true Aſcenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Lordes bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, that aroſe a body and no ſpirite, and of his place vvhether he vvent to be in. 25</item>
                  <label>CHAP. 7.</label>
                  <item>The diuers ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of this vvorde, Heauen, as it is vſed in ſcripture. 38</item>
                  <label>CHAP. 8.</label>
                  <item>VVhat Gods righte hand is, and to vvho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <pb facs="tcp:10:127"/>
it is referred. 45</item>
                  <label>CHAP. 9.</label>
                  <item>VVhat it is to ſit at the righte hande of God, hovve Chriſte ſitteth ther, &amp; vvhat he dothe. 48</item>
                  <label>CHAP. 10.</label>
                  <item>That Chriſte ſitteth at the right hande of God by his humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye, but circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcribed in place, and is not euery vhere. 52</item>
                  <label>CHAP. 11.</label>
                  <item>An other ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſitting at the right hande of God, by vvhich maner of ſitting Chriſt is eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vvher, ſitting ther in ſuch ſorte after his Godhead. 71</item>
                  <label>CHAP. 12.</label>
                  <item>The frute and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditye of the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Aſcenſion of Chriſt, bothe in that he doth novv for vs, and in that vve learn by it. 76</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>The ſecond part.</head>
               <list>
                  <label>CHAP. 13.</label>
                  <item>Of the true Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of our flesh. 85</item>
                  <label>CHAP. 14.</label>
                  <item>Our fleshe, or bodye it ſelfe, shall riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, thoughe it be harde to beleue, and vvhat the fleshe or body is. 89</item>
                  <label>CHAP. 15.</label>
                  <item>The maner hovv the bodies shall riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and the kinde that they shall be of. 114</item>
                  <label>
                     <pb facs="tcp:10:127"/>CHAP. 16.</label>
                  <item>That Paul ſpake right<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly of a glorified bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and vvhat a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified bodye is, and vvhat a natural. 121</item>
                  <label>CHAP. 17.</label>
                  <item>The caſe of our me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers in the bodyes reſurrection, and of their functions. 134</item>
                  <label>CHAP. 18.</label>
                  <item>The diuers erroures that ſprong aboute the article of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 138</item>
                  <label>CHAP. 19.</label>
                  <item>The erroures of Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen concerning the reſurrection, confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Hierom. 143</item>
                  <label>CHAP. 20.</label>
                  <item>S. Hieromes opinion of the reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the fleshe. 149</item>
                  <label>CHAP. 21.</label>
                  <item>S. Auguſtines minde of the reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the fleshe. 152</item>
                  <label>CHAP. 22.</label>
                  <item>VVhat Aurelius Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencius thoughte of the ſame. 156</item>
                  <label>CHAP. 23.</label>
                  <item>The bodies of vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuers shall verelye riſe againe. 159</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>The third part.</head>
               <list>
                  <label>CHAP. 24.</label>
                  <item>The death and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the vngod<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly. 171</item>
                  <label>CHAP. 25.</label>
                  <item>That there is an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall death and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and that the ſoule is paſſible. 175</item>
                  <label>CHAP. 26.</label>
                  <item>The bodies of the vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>beleeuers, being rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,
<pb facs="tcp:10:128"/>
are paſſible. 179</item>
                  <label>CHAP. 27.</label>
                  <item>The paines of Hell, &amp; the matter for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinuance of the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, vvith the ſpace of the place &amp; kinds of punishments. 186</item>
                  <label>CHAP. 28.</label>
                  <item>The Refutation of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that denied the punishmente of the vngodly to be eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall. 194</item>
                  <label>CHAP 29.</label>
                  <item>Of eternal life &amp; ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, and that ther is an eternal life. 203</item>
                  <label>CHAP. 30.</label>
                  <item>VVhere the place of the faithfull is. 207</item>
                  <label>CHAP. 31.</label>
                  <item>Hovve the ſaluation shall be. 210</item>
                  <label>CHAP. 32.</label>
                  <item>The ſoules departed, vvot not vvhat they do that ar aliue, ther by anye thing to be diſquieted. 226</item>
                  <label>CHAP. 33.</label>
                  <item>The Faithfull shall knovve one an other in heauen. 231</item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:10:128"/>
            <figure>
               <head>GOD IS MY HELPER</head>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>PRINTED at London in Crede</hi> Lane, by Hugh Singleton, at the ſigne of the Golden Tunne.</p>
            <p>ANNO. 1574.</p>
            <p>Cum priuilegio ad impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendum ſolum.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
